<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The king's authority in dispensing with ecclesiastical laws, asserted and vindicated by the late Reverend Philip Nye ...</title>
            <title>Lawfulnes of the oath of supremacy and power of the King in ecclesiastical affairs</title>
            <author>Nye, Philip, 1596?-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17198</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11861817</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11861817</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50015</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52597)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50015)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 503:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The king's authority in dispensing with ecclesiastical laws, asserted and vindicated by the late Reverend Philip Nye ...</title>
                  <title>Lawfulnes of the oath of supremacy and power of the King in ecclesiastical affairs</title>
                  <author>Nye, Philip, 1596?-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H.N. and Nathanael Ranew ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Published by the author's son, Henry Nye.</note>
                  <note>Published in 1683 under title: The lawfulnes of the oath of supremacy and power of the king in ecclesiastical affairs.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Ecclesiastical law --  England.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50015:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE King's Authority In DISPENSING with <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Laws,</hi> Aſſerted and Vindicated.</p>
            <p>By the late Reverend <hi>PHILIP NYE,</hi> A Congregational Divine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed for <hi>H. N.</hi> and <hi>Nathanael Ranew,</hi> at the King's Arms in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, MDCLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50015:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50015:2"/>
            <head>TO THE King's moſt Excellent Majeſty, JAMES, By the Grace of God, Of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> KING, Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Majeſty;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOUR Gracious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> is ſuch an inſtance of the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der care You have of each Man that hath the happineſs to be Your Subject, that it as well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acts
<pb facs="tcp:50015:3"/>the Service of every one in particular, as the Univerſal Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Great Sir,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having no better opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to expreſs my Gratitude, I lay at Your Royal Feet theſe Sheets, wrote by my deceaſed Father, occaſioned by his late Majeſty's Declaration. May they be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental to promote the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Your Princely Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; May every Individual in Your Kingdoms, enjoy their Conſciences and Property; May your Parliaments ſerve you in all thoſe healthful Laws which
<pb facs="tcp:50015:3"/>may appeaſe our Differences, and ſecure our Peace; ſo that not only the preſent Age, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Poſterity, may bleſs your Reign for introducing ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsionate an Indulgence. Theſe Bleſsings for you, and us; and that you may live long and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily in the purſuance of theſe merciful and noble Principles, are the Prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſty's moſt obedient Subject, <hi>HENRY NYE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50015:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50015:4"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE of Eccleſiaſtical Laws, and Supremacy of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> in Diſpenſing with the Penalties of ſuch Laws.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Caſe and State of the Queſtion.</head>
               <p>THE King's Power and Juriſdiction in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, may fall under a three-fold Conſideration: as, Firſt, put forth by himſelf; Secondly, by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion granted to Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in thoſe Courts we term Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical. Thirdly, Or ſuch Affairs are managed and ordered by him in Parliament, and the Authority thereof.</p>
               <p>The Form in which theſe Eccleſiaſtical Laws are expreſſed unto us, is this; <q>Be it enacted by the King's moſt excellent Majeſty, by and with the Advice and Conſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in Parliament aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by the Authority of the ſame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Meerly to adviſe and conſent, imply no more Authority in the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Eccleſiaſtical Laws, than what was put forth in the Convocation in their Canons; but it being added, <hi>by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the ſame,</hi> this Authority thus mentioned, may be conſtrued, either relating to the Advice and Conſent of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50015:5"/>Lords and Commons in Parliament, a Suffrage more than an Advice or bare Conſent; for it implieth, when Bills are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, read, debated, and aſſented to by both Houſes, they were then ſtamped with ſome kind of Parliamentary Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: Or it is to be interpreted, relating to King, Lords, and Commons; and which is likely, for Conſultations of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, tho concluded by Vote, yet become not formally a Law, until his Majeſty hath given his Royal Aſſent.</p>
               <p>And in this ſenſe, Eccleſiaſtical Laws and Orders, which are Enacted and Eſtabliſhed by Statutes, have as formal a Sanction (being not only by Authority of the King, but by Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament) as other Laws wherein our Civil Intereſts are concerned, namely, a joint, and not the ſingle Power of either.</p>
               <p>This being granted, (rather than needleſly to diſpute thoſe higheſt Intereſts) and thence alſo inferred, That as theſe Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Laws have their Riſe, Vigour, and Strength, ſo their Diminution and Abatement from conjunction of both Powers; and are more fixed and ſtable than thoſe Canons and Orders in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, that have their Sanction from the King only.</p>
               <p>To this I ſay briefly; <hi>Altho Men may be Tenants in Common, yet none can be joint Tenants with the King.</hi> Theſe Powers are not equal, the King hath the Supremacy, and is thereby enabled to ſuch Acts and Orderings about the Penalties of our Laws, as are peculiar to the Crown and Dignity of a King; as in Mitigating, Exempting, Diſpenſing, Licenſing, Pardoning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all this more eſpecially in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, as by the following Diſcourſe will appear.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>This Power and Superiority exerciſed by the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> in relation to the Penalties of ſuch Penal Laws of both ſorts ſhall be ſpoken to in theſe two Particulars.</p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50015:5"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. That ſuch an Authority and Supremacy is neceſſary, and ought to be placed in ſome Hand.</item>
                     <item>II. That it is a Dignity which hath always been placed in the Kings and Queens of this Realm.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">I. For the former; In all Polities and Forms of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as there is a Rule which is to be the Meaſure and Square to, and by which all Mens Actions that live under that Polity, are ordinarily to be conformed and judged; ſo is there always ſome proviſion made for mitigating the Rigour of the Rule, in Caſes which may fall out and cannot be foreſeen by the wiſeſt Legiſlators; and in ſuch caſes to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe <hi>Summum jus,</hi> would be <hi>Summa injuria:</hi> therefore there is here, not only a Power to judg, as the caſe ſtands in the ſtrict Letter of the Law, but as there are Courts of Law, ſo are there Chanceries, Courts of Equity and Conſcience, wherein the Law and Rule it ſelf is diſpenſed with, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried from; and the Proceedings there are not according to the ſtrict Terms of Law, but <hi>ſecundum equum &amp; bonum,</hi> as the Merit of the Caſe in it ſelf may require.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For Laws conſtituted for a whole Nation univerſally, to be ſubmitted to by Perſons of what quality ſoever, and how much ſoever different in their Conditions, muſt needs, in their ſtrict execution, bear harder upon ſome Men than others, Parliaments in their Laws going by the Rule of (<hi>Ad ea quae frequentius accidunt,</hi> &amp;c.) and better an inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Miſchief, than an Inconvenience.</p>
                  <p>It is taken for granted, that a general Law which hath its Good and Neceſſity, in reſpect to the Bulk and Body of a People, may prove unequal to particular Perſons from the Circumſtances of their preſent Condition. In a Common Wealth the Eaſe and Benefit of each particular Perſon, of what Degree or Condition ſoever, is to be conſulted; but where Laws are executed in their full rigour, and no Mercy or Indulgence to particular Perſons, in ſpecial and unuſual
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50015:6"/>Caſes, it will not be ſo. God himſelf, who knoweth every Man's Heart, yet ſome of his Laws that are given in general to all, would not prove ſo equal to each at all times, without exemptions in particular Caſes. Hence we ſay, Affirmative Precepts bind not <hi>ad ſemper;</hi> to ſuch Laws is that of <hi>Mark</hi> 2.26. in the Caſe of Shew-bread to be referred. And the Pope, who aſſumes to himſelf a poſſibility not to Err, yet how doth his Republick abound in Courts for Faculties, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, Indulgences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. It's alſo to be conſidered, there are no Societies of Men but may err in their Councils; Laws made in one Parliament come to a Review, and often to an Alteration, yea Repeal in the next: The Intervals of thoſe great Councils are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times long, and if no way of Relief were in the mean time, the Subject would, without Remedy, undergo the penalty of an unequal Law.</p>
                  <p>Theſe and the like Conſiderations make it neceſſary, that beſides the Legiſlative Power placed in the Parliament, that there be ſome Hand or other alſo, by which upon all emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Occaſions, the rigour of a Law as to its Penalty may be abated, by the means whereof, not only Mens Liberties and Eſtates, but Lives alſo are ſometimes preſerved.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="2">2. This Ballance hath always been truſted in the Hand, and annexed to the Sovereign Majeſty of every State; for this Intereſt doth little vary, but remaineth in a manner the ſame in all Republicks, in what Form ſoever they be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed. In the State of <hi>England,</hi> being an Empire, and its Crown in many Acts of Parliament (eſpecially relating to theſe Matters) ſtiled Imperial; this Power is inſeparably annexed thereunto, which needs little proof, it being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Oath of Supremacy. An Oath is the End of a Controverſy. Our great Lawyers alſo give in their Suffrage
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50015:6"/>hereunto, frequently affirming that the Statutes relating to the King's Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, are not introductive of New, but declarative of the old Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When an Act, ſay both thoſe two Learned Judges,</hi> Cooke <hi>and</hi> Rolls, <hi>forbiddeth under a Penalty, in caſe it may be inconvenient to divers particular Perſons, in reſpect of Circumſtances, the Law gives Power to the King to diſpenſe therewith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in like Caſes, or upon other Conſiderations equal, he may Diſpenſe, Licenſe, Pardon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea, although thoſe Laws have been paſſed by his Majeſty's Royal Aſſent former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and (which is more) a Clauſe inſerted in the Act, that the King's Licence or Diſpenſation in this or that Caſe, ſhall be void: Yet it will be no Bar to ſuch Prerogatives as are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent and originally inſeparable to his Royal Perſon, but he may give Licence with a <hi>Non Obſtante</hi> thereunto. A learned Serjeant, in his <hi>Nomotechina,</hi> hath theſe words, <hi>The King by a Clauſe of</hi> Non Obſtante, <hi>may diſpenſe with a Statute Law, if he recite the Statute, though the Statute ſay ſuch Diſpenſations ſhall be merely void. And he may Licenſe Things forbidden by the Statutes, as to coin Mony, which is made a Capital Offence by the Statute, and was before lawful,</hi> for that it is but <hi>malum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitum; but</hi> malum in ſe, <hi>as to leave a Nuſance in the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, he cannot licenſe to do; but when it is done he may pardon it; but where the Statute ſaith, his Licenſe ſhall be void, which the Civilians call</hi> Clauſula derogativa, <hi>there it muſt have a Clauſe of</hi> Non Obſtante, <hi>that is to ſay, this Clauſe notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Statute, elſe it is not good.</hi> And ſays the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, <hi>He may, in reſpect of his Supream Eccleſiaſtical Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, exempt ſome from the Juriſdiction of the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and diſpenſe with others in things which the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Law prohibits, upon the ſame ground that they are not</hi> mala in ſe, <hi>but</hi> prohibita. <hi>I hold clear</hi> (ſaith Judg <hi>Hobart</hi>) <hi>that though the Statute ſays, That all Diſpenſations,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall be granted in manner and form following, and not otherwiſe; that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50015:7"/>yet the King is not thereby reſtrained, but his Power remains full and perfect as before; and he may ſtill grant them as King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The King may remit the Penalty or Puniſhment of thoſe Laws, which he hath no power to diſpenſe with, as where what is forbidden by the Law is <hi>Malum in ſe,</hi> ſaith the Serjeant in his aformentioned Diſcourſe of Law, much more then when what is forbiden is only <hi>Malum prohibitum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Statute indeed of the <hi>9th</hi> of <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. enacts, That no Letter ſhall proceed from the King to diſcharge an Excommunicated Perſon, but where the King's Liberty is prejudiced: But as this Statute it ſelf proves the Law and former Practice, ſo it takes it not away, ſince the King's Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of diſcharging ſuch Perſons uſed before, is preſerved by the ſame Statute.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Prerogatives and Regal Powers, in Relation to Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Laws, and Matters of Religion.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. REligion in the moral Parts thereof, the Precepts and Commandments of God, the Inſtitutions and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt, theſe are not ſubject to any Humane Wiſdom or Power. The Apoſtles, that were of higher Authority in theſe Affairs than any on Earth, went no farther, but as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. <hi>What I have received of the Lord, that I delivered unto you.</hi> To make Laws in Spiritual Matters, that are ſuch by the Light of Nature, that Men may be moved to Duty, and act according to their Light, we yield to the Civil Magiſtrate as he is <hi>Cuſtos utriuſque Tabulae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:50015:7"/>
                  <p n="2">2. There are Matters of Circumſtance alſo, and <hi>external Forms in Worſhip, tending to Order and Decency:</hi> Theſe and the like are made by our Laws, to depend upon the Power and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of the Prince. This Diſtinction you have laid down as Law by Judg <hi>Hobart;</hi> his words are theſe: <hi>Tho it be</hi> de Jure Divino, <hi>that Chriſtian People be provided of Chriſtian Offices and Duties, of Teaching, Adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the like; and of Paſtors for that purpoſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to debar them wholly of it, were expreſly againſt the Law of God; yet the Diſtinction of Pariſhes, and the Form of furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every Pariſh Church with his proper Curat, Rector, or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, by the way of Preſentation, Inſtitution,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as is uſed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly in divers Churches; and the State or Title which he hath, or is to have in his Church, or Benefice, is not a poſitive Law of God in point of Circumſtance. And we know well that the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church in its greateſt Purity, were but voluntary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations of Believers, ſubmitting themſelves to the Apoſtles, and after to other Paſtors, to whom they did miniſter of their Temporals as God did move them.</hi> Government is a Beam of Divine Power, and therefore he proceeds, ſaying, <hi>If a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will refuſe all Government, it were againſt the Law of God; but if a Popular State will receive a Monarchy, it ſtands well with the Law of God. In the Caſe of</hi> Glover <hi>and</hi> Colt, <hi>againſt the Biſhop of</hi> Coventry <hi>and</hi> Litchfield.</p>
                  <p>From all this the Judg ſeems to confirm his Diſtinction by way of Compariſon thus; As in Humane Affairs, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the General and Eſſentials of it, (that one Man be Subject to another Man in an orderly way) is neceſſary and <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> and not in Man's Liberty or Diſpoſe; But for the Modes and Forms of Government, and like Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, it is left to the wiſdom and choice of Men, and the conduct thereof. So in Matters of Religion, what is not <hi>Jure Divino, ſuch external Forms and Rites tending to a more orderly and decent adminiſtration in the Worſhip and Service of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50015:8"/>God,</hi> our Law judgeth the Magiſtrate hath the ordering hereof in each Nation, according to the Manners and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the People, which is Various.</p>
                  <p>And in particular, the Diſpoſing of Paſtors and People, for the more convenient and orderly Service and Worſhip of God, to be only <hi>Jure Humano,</hi> and may be otherwiſe, and was ſo in the Primitive Church in her greateſt purity. Paſtors and People were not then (as now) engaged in this Relation, and one to another, by a Parochial Bond or Tye: but injoyed a Chriſtian Liberty, voluntarily to diſpoſe of themſelves under ſuch or ſuch a Miniſtry as they ſhould make choiſe of to themſelves. The Church is ſaid in this State to be in greateſt purity. The Congregational-way therefore is not a way (in this learned Judg's Opinion) of Diſorder and Confuſion, as is frequently ſuggeſted.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And that it is in the Power of Supream Majeſty to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with a Pariſhioner, as well as with a Paſtor or Rector, <hi>in ſuch a Caſe, that is, to remove from his Pariſh to another, for more ſuitable Enjoyments, as for a Rector upon his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Diſpenſation,</hi> to be a Non-reſident and take another Recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the diviſion of Pariſhes being <hi>Jure Humano.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What thoſe Things and Matters of Religion are (in the Judgment of our State) that comes under the Manage of humane Wiſdom and Power, are well expreſſed in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Advertiſement. <hi>Theſe Orders and Rules enſuing have been meet and convenient to be uſed and followed; yet not preſcribing theſe Rules as Laws, equivalent with the Eternal Word of God, and as of neceſſity to bind the Conſciences of our Subjects, in the nature of them, conſidered in themſelves; Or as they ſhould add any Efficacy, or more Holineſs to the Vertue of Publick Prayer, and to the Sacraments, but as temporal Orders, meerly Eccleſiaſtical, without any vain Superſtition, and as Rules in ſome part of Diſcipline, concerning Decencies, Diſtinction and Order for the time.</hi> And in the Articles of 1562, <hi>It is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50015:8"/>not neceſſary that Traditions and Ceremonies be in all Places one, or utterly alike; for at all times they have been divers, and may be changed according to the diverſity of Countries and Mens Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſo that nothing be ordained againſt God's Word.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is granted, that even theſe Eccleſiaſtical Laws ought to be conformable to the Word of God, and to thoſe General Rules (laid down in the Scriptures for ordering the Worſhip and Service of God in the Churches) as, <hi>Let all things be done decently and to Edification; Give no offence to Jew or Gentile,</hi> and the like, and not to be the meer inventions of Men.</p>
                  <p>That diſtinction ſome would make of things <hi>againſt,</hi> or contrary, and what is <hi>according</hi> to the Word of God, the one they apply to Matters of Faith, the other to Matters of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. It is a Diſtinction without a Difference; there is more Wit than Truth in that Interpretation of Chriſt's Words, <hi>He that is not with me, is againſt me;</hi> and in another place, <hi>he that is not againſt me, is with me;</hi> applying the one to Matters of Faith, the other to Matters of Order. There is no ſuch diſtinction to be made, but Rites, Ceremonies, and Matters of Order, ought to be according to God's Word, as well as Matters of Faith. Magiſtrates are to judg, <hi>Circa Res Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias de iis ſi Fidei ſint dogmata, Vel ritus et Ceremoniae earum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Veritatem et Equitatem; juxta Verbi Divini normam</hi> (Mocket <hi>de pol. Eccl. Angl. cap.</hi> 3.) And the Power of the King ſtands not in forming new Articles of Faith, or Forms of Religion, ſuch as were <hi>Jeroboam's Calves;</hi> but in defending and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating that Faith and Religion, of which God in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is the undoubted Author, (ſaith <hi>Maſon</hi> of Biſhops, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.)</p>
                  <p>It is evident thoſe Holy Men, our firſt Reformers, made no ſuch diſtinction, but that all ſhould be done <hi>according</hi> to God's Word, laying before them theſe general Rules in Scripture, (even in retaining what hath been ſo offenſive). For of the retaining Ceremonies, there is this account by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50015:9"/>them given, <hi>Becauſe they appertain to Edification; whereunto all things done in the Church, as the Apoſtle teacheth, ought to be referred.</hi> And of our <hi>Liturgy,</hi> thus; <hi>There is nothing to be read but the very pure Word of God, and the Holy Scriptures, or that which is evidently grounded upon the ſame,</hi> (Preface to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer Book). <hi>God be thanked</hi> (ſaith good King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the <hi>6th</hi>) <hi>we know both what by his Word is meet to be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and have amended,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>It is convenient thus diſtinctly to have inſiſted upon what we term Religion, or Matters Eccleſiaſtical, according to that ſenſe in which the Civil Magiſtrate aſſumes to himſelf the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering thereof: And what influence the Scriptures, and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of God, hath, or ought to have in theſe Rites of the Church, and Matters of Order, as well as in Matters of Faith; for hereby it appears whence it is Mens Conſciences are more concerned in theſe Laws, than in other Municipal Laws of the Nation. And that the not being free to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to theſe Eccleſiaſtical Laws, when not formed according to God's Word, is no Evidence of that Seditious Spirit that kicks againſt all Laws.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>There is a neceſſity, and that of much greater importance, Proviſions be made of Diſpenſations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as occaſion ſhall be, in reſpect to Laws Eccleſiaſtical, than in Civil.</p>
                  <p>In Matters of Religion, and the Worſhip of God:
<list>
                        <item>1. Multitudes there are of looſe and profane Perſons; in reſpect to ſuch, neither are the Laws in themſelves, nor in the execution of them, ſevere enough.</item>
                        <item>2. Againſt Popiſh Recuſants the Laws have been ſevere e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, yet in the execution great moderation.</item>
                        <item>3. There are thoſe, and bleſſed be God great Multitudes, who are not only Orthodox in Faith, but of unblamable
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50015:9"/>Life in the greater Things of Law and Goſpel. Theſe are fallen under moſt ſevere Laws, and of late with greateſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity put in execution, and utterly ruin'd, if there be no means of relaxation: It is in behalf of theſe I argue this Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, and that from theſe and the like Conſiderations.
<list>
                              <item>1. There is a greater proneneſs in Conſcientious Men to ſcruple and to be doubtful in their Obedience to the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, than to the Civil Laws of a Nation, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</item>
                              <item>2. Great Difficulty in forming Laws, wherein Mens Conſciences are immediately concern'd, ſo as not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfy ſome, if not many.</item>
                              <item>3. If thoſe Laws be not according to Scripture, in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of thoſe that are to obey, whatſoever they are in themſelves, it is our Sin if we obey; it is not ſo in Civil Commands.</item>
                              <item>4. It is not of ſo ill Conſequence for us to yield Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to a Civil, as to an Eccleſiaſtical Law, if ill conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by the State.</item>
                              <item>5. From what is found (in a manner peculiar in theſe our Eccleſiaſtical Laws, and the Adminiſtration of them) many ways prejudicial to the Subject, there is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity ſome ſuch proviſion of this kind be found on our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. The real Scruples and Doubts about our Obedience in theſe Eccleſiaſtical Matters, cannot but be more and greater than in other Laws. The knowingeſt Man in theſe Things knoweth but in part; and the moſt Men have but a parcel
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50015:10"/>in this part. It is true, the Principles and great Matters of Religion, are in great perſpicuity laid down in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which give knowledg to the Simple, but theſe matter of Circumſtance and external Order, we have for the moſt part in Generals only, and hints from Examples and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of the Apoſtolick Churches; in the interpretation whereof the moſt Learned find Difficulties, and are divided. Now the want of Knowledg is the ground of Scruples and Doubts in our Practice, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.7. for the working of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is from the ultimate Reſolution of our practical Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. And hence it is that the ſame practice may be not only ſcrupled, but a Sin to one Man which is not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, upon account of different Apprehenſions; there may be notwithſtanding Integrity and Sincerity in both, and therefore tenderly to be dealt with, as the Apoſtle requires, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A great Difficulty there is to form Eccleſiaſtical Laws (they being to be the ſame where Uniformity is much ſtood upon for a whole Nation) as not to leave grounds of Diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to many; Mens Apprehenſions being various through the Degrees of Light; inſomuch as that may be Sin to one Man, that is a Liberty to another of a greater degree of Light. A little is next to nothing, and what is indifferent is neareſt in likeneſs to moral Good or Evil; hence ſo eaſy and frequent Miſtakings: And as it is with particular Perſons, ſo may it be with a Society or Company of Men. One true Church in theſe Things differing from another, and the ſame Church differs from it ſelf upon further Diſcoveries. A Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, a Parliament, they may judg ſuch and ſuch Things to be indifferent, that thoſe that are to ſubmit may ſincerely ſcruple and ſtick at as Sin. If Churches and Men, ſavingly enlightned, are thus expoſed to vary in their Apprehenſions, we cannot be confident of any Council or Aſſembly made up
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50015:10"/>of the moſt wiſe and prudent Men. Parliaments are choſen by Vote of the promiſcuous Multitude, with reſpect (we would hope) to their Sufficiency in managing of our Civil and Temporal Concerns, but their Skill and Ability to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern and judg of Matters appertaining to Order in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Worſhip of God, all Men have not this Knowledg, this is little or not at all attended by thoſe that elect them; by reaſon whereof, Matters wherein Mens Conſciences are concerned, are not at all times carried by thoſe that are moſt Conſcientious in that Aſſembly, who are not always the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part, yet notwithſtanding are engaged in their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to aſſent and conſent to ſuch Determinations being made, though poſſibly near one half in number diſſented in the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them; and it is unavoidable in all and the beſt Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies that are choſen by the general Suffrage of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Again, theſe Matters of Ceremony, and External Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, are ſometimes managed in part with reſpect to a Party different in their Apprehenſions, and thereupon form thoſe Laws, with reſpect to Prudence as well as Conſcience. In our firſt Reformation, it is ſaid, ſuch Superſtitions are taken away, <hi>as Time would ſerve quietly to do it.</hi> And many things were left remaining in our Liturgy, (which otherwiſe would have been removed) in compliance with that Form of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service, uſed before by the Papiſts, that they may not be provoked, but rather won thereby to our Religion. Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens baptizing was continued in our <hi>Liturgy</hi> (ſaith the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi>) elſe the Book would not have paſſed the Houſe, (Conference at <hi>Hampton Court).</hi> King <hi>James</hi> was once willing, that ſome Ceremonies giving Offence ſhould be removed; but the Parliament then ſitting thought it not prudent. And our Gracious King would have done a greater Matter for the Eaſe of Tender Conſciences, (as appears by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50015:11"/>ſome of the Declarations herein after mentioned) but it ſtood not with the Prudence of the Houſe, as they expreſſed in their Anſwer; without whoſe Concurrence his Majeſty thought not fit then to do it.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. From miſtaken Principles: As that there can be no Unity without Uniformity; there can be no Diſcipline in a Church, without ſome Ceremonies of Humane Inſtitution. Things indifferent become neceſſary in Worſhip, being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by Authority; what Things in matters of Order are once eſtabliſhed, and ſometimes continued in the Church, may not with ſafety be altered.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Things I offer not to derogate from Parliaments in their manage of ſuch Affairs, but upon this ſerious Account only, To ſhew, that as our Civil Laws have made proviſion that the Church ſhall not in their Laws and Canons, order any Thing againſt Prerogative of the King, or the Laws and Statutes of this Realm in general, and that ſuch Canons ſhall not be in force, (25 <hi>H.</hi> 8.19.) So likewiſe Laws and Statutes in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, eſtabliſhed by the Civil Power, if they be found to derogate from the Prerogative of Chriſt Jeſus, or the Laws and Inſtitutions of his Kingdom, ought not to be in force upon Mens Conſciences. As Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men being ſuppoſed not to be ſo well underſtood in Secular Laws, but may tranſgreſs; ſo may Secular Perſons likewiſe, in their ordering about Church Affairs: There is therefore the like neceſſity of a Power to review, judg, and diſpenſe with ſuch Laws as ſhall be found to diſturb the Conſciences of peaceable Subjects, as occaſion may urge thereunto. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. by Commiſſion (which was continued by <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.) appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thirty two Perſons, eight of each Profeſſion, to peruſe the Canons of the Clergy then in force, to the end thoſe might be removed that were any ways againſt the Crown and State. Thoſe Kings might have done the like, in reſpect
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50015:11"/>to thoſe Canons and Eccleſiaſtical Laws enacted in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if they be found to derogate from Chriſt or his Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, or juſtly offenſive to the Peaceable and Godly, that Diſpenſations might be granted for the preſent, until farther Reformation be obtained.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Municipal Laws of a Nation, are from and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the Principles of Right Reaſon and Common Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice only; and we have ſubmitted our ſelves to the Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thoſe wiſe and prudent Senators we our ſelves have made choice of, to enact and eſtabliſh ſuch Laws for us, and therefore may acquieſce in their Determinations without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inquiry, having given a kind of abſolute pre-conſent to ſuch Laws as ſhall be enacted by them.</p>
                  <p>But it is not ſo in Eccleſiaſtical Laws entruſted with the ſame Perſons, for as they are to be formed according to God's Word, which every Man is to take as his immediate Rule, and not to do or ſubmit to any thing in his practice that hath the Notion of Religion, but what is conformable thereunto, he is to live and act by his own Faith. To Laws Eccleſiaſtical therefore made in Parliament, we give only a conditional Conſent, that is, <hi>a Conſent to them ſo far as they are agreeable to God's Word, and concur with Goſpel-Rules.</hi> Nor is it in the liberty of any Man's Conſcience or Reaſon to yield more, nor is there any more intruſted by us with our Repreſentative, the Parliament. If a Man doth ſcruple the Reaſonableneſs or Equity of a Law concerning Civil Rights, or what's required from it, he may notwithſtanding yield Obedience without Sin; and ought ſo to do, rather than to offend by an appearance of Diſobedience, as Chriſt himſelf did, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.26, 27. But in Matters of Religion, even as Circumſtances, Ceremonies, or the leaſt thing wherein
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50015:12"/>the Lord hath concerned his Word; if there be a Doubt or Scruple, whether lawful and conformable to the Scriptures, tho it be from Ignorance or Weakneſs, yet I ſin if I ſubmit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1. compared with 23.</p>
                  <p>The Conſequence of Tranſgreſſion in this kind, is more than loſs of Eſtates, Liberties, yea or of Life it ſelf. If the Laws of Superiors, concerning Civil Rights, be unjuſt in themſelves, or prove unequal from the Circumſtances of this or that Man's Caſe, who cannot be relieved by any Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, he may ſubmit without Sin, without tranſgreſſing any Law of God; nay, it is Vertue, and pleaſing to the Lord, our patience in ſuch ſuffering, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. with verſes 18, 19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.7. but not ſo in the Matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, for we have from Chriſt to the contrary, that is, not to ſubject, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.20. And God blames his People by his Prophets, <hi>for wittingly walking after the Commandments,</hi> Hoſ. 5.12. and for <hi>keeping the Statutes of</hi> Omri, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.16. the Lord is a jealous God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>If there be not a Power to Judg and Diſpenſe intruſted in ſome Hands, the People of God are in a worſe condition on theſe Accounts, than in their Civil Intereſt, and that upon a three-fold account.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Secular Laws and Statutes made in the behalf of the Subjects, are often, upon further Deliberation and Experience of Inconveniencies, altered and repealed, whereby the Subjects have eaſe: But Acts of Parliament, wherein Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, and Mens Conſciences are concern'd, are ſeldom or never reviſed or altered, much leſs repealed; no not for the ſpace of an hundred Years can we give an Inſtance hereof. So far are we from repealing Acts made in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, as is ordinarily in our Civil
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50015:12"/>Matters, that ſome Acts paſſed partly for their Severity, or upon ſome other Account, doubtful whether fit to remain as ſtanding Laws, therefore are limited to a certain Time, after which to expire and ceaſe: the ſevere Act of 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> that in the Proceſs of it reached Mens Lives, when firſt paſſed, was to remain a Law but to the end of the next Seſſion of Parliament, which in regard of ſome Doubt it ſeems made whether in Force or not, is declared by the preſent Parliament to be in Force, and ought to be put in due execution. And now at this time there is a Miniſter of the Goſpel under the Sentence of that Act; and for tranſgreſſing that Law, had loſt his Life, had not his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty interpoſed by his Prerogative. A wiſe Stateſman once adviſed and expreſſed himſelf thus: <hi>I ask why the Civil State ſhould be purged and reſtored, with good and wholſom Laws made in every three or four Years in Parliament, providing Remedies as faſt as time breedeth Miſchiefs; and contrariwiſe, the Eccleſiaſtical State ſhould ſtill continue upon the Dregs of Time, and receive no Alteration now for theſe many Years? We have heard of no offer of Bills in Parliament; is it becauſe there is nothing amiſs?</hi> Sir. <hi>Fr. Bacon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In that all Proceedings in Eccleſiaſtical Courts, are ever to the utmoſt rigour of the Letter of their Canons and Orders; there is no Chancery or Court of Equity among them to appeal unto for Redreſs; but in ſome few Caſes (as in Cauſes Teſtimentary, of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, Divorſes, Tythes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſpecified, 24 <hi>H.</hi> 8.12. Matters wherein our Eſtates are touched), But in Matters of Conformity, and ſuch Caſes wherein our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences are moſt concerned, we are left deſtitute.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Again, Men are upon this peculiar diſadvantage in theſe Spiritual Courts, who are impeached for Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50015:13"/>to their Canons and Orders, in that their Adverſaries, and thoſe that are Parties, for the moſt part are their Judge; this Sir <hi>Fra. Bacon,</hi> in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, condemned as a great Injuſtice: So that it is evident, conſidering the Nature of Eccleſiaſtical Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, and how managed with us in this Nation; how neceſſary it is that ſome Power be placed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, by which we may not be expoſed more than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to ſuch extremity of Rigour; for otherwiſe, as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciencious Men are more diſpoſed to Scruples and Doubts in the way of Duty in this kind, ſo to leſs Mercy and Indulgence from our Superiors.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:50015:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> That our Relief is from the Juriſdiction and Power in his Majeſty, to Diſpenſe and Exempt; for in his Hand this Ballance is placed; which is that we ſhall inſist up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the next place.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THIS Prerogative or Power, to Diſpenſe and Exempt from Eccleſiaſtical Laws, is in the Soveraign; for the Confirmation whereof, not to inſiſt on what was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by Pope <hi>Eleutherius</hi> touching <hi>Lucius</hi> our firſt Chriſtian King, that he was <hi>Vicarius Dei in Regno ſuo,</hi> in reference to Matters to be reformed; or is mentioned touching the Laws and Practice of King <hi>Edgar,</hi> and <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Confeſſor named the Firſt; <hi>Meae ſolicitudinis eſt quieti eorum conſulare, de quorum moribus ſpectat ad nos exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> And of the other (from whom it is ſaid much of our Law is derived) that deſcribing the King's Office, he ſaith; <hi>Rex ad hoc eſt conſtitutus ut Regnum terrenum, Populum Dei &amp; Eccleſiam regat, &amp; ab injuriis defendat, &amp; maleficos ab eâ evallat, deſtruat, &amp; penitus deſperdat,</hi> and much of like nature that might be urg'd from Antiquity. But to come nearer Home.</p>
                  <p>The Teſtimonies of the Clergy in Convocation, the Repreſentative Church of <hi>England,</hi> who make it ſo great a Duty to acknowledg it, as they have expreſſed their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity thus; <hi>Whoſoevor ſhall affirm the King's Majeſty hath
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50015:14"/>not the ſame Authority in Cauſe Eccleſiaſtical, as the pious Princes of the Jews, and the Chriſtian Emperors obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>let him be Excommunicated,</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>and not to be abſolved but by the Arch-biſhop of</hi> Canterbury. (Canons of the Convocation, 1603.)</p>
                  <p n="2">2. I ſhall join with this Teſtimony, that of another Synod or Council, namely, that met in the <hi>Star Chamber,</hi> (a.<hi>Jac.</hi>) made up of all the Judges and Perſons learned in the Law, ſummoned by King <hi>James</hi> for Reſolution in ſome Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes, whereof this of his Majeſty's Prerogative was one; their Reſolution you have in theſe words; <hi>The King may, without the Parliament, make Orders and Conſtitutions for the Government of the Clergy, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thoſe that diſobey or refuſe to ſubmit.</hi> And this, with other Reſolutions in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, were ordered to be regiſtred and recorded in the ſeveral Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And from time to time, the Kings and Queens of <hi>England,</hi> have aſſumed and exerciſed this Power, <hi>and there hath been no matter or thing ſo Sacred, and of ſuch Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in theſe Affairs ordered by Parliament, but the like, and of as great importance by the King alone, with advice of his Council, Inſtances whereof you have many.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. In general; The whole Syſtem and Body of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Laws and Canons are publiſhed by the Synods of the Clergy from time to time: <hi>Theſe Laws have no Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Sanction, or dependance upon Authority thence derived an their Conſtitution.</hi> Nor yet have theſe Canons their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from the Synod or Clergy met in Convocation; for Canons concluded by the Province of <hi>Canterbury</hi> only, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not oblige the Clergy of the Province of <hi>York,</hi> having no Repreſentatives or Clerks ſitting in that Synod; ſuch was the Synod or Convocation met <hi>Anno</hi> 1584, 1597, 1603,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50015:14"/>and yet obliged to Subjection, the Arch-Biſhop and Clergy of the Province of <hi>York</hi> as well as thoſe of 1640: where were the Repreſentatives of both Provinces? It's therefore the Regal Authority expreſs'd in the Letters Patents affixed to theſe Canons, that gives them their chief Power, and are therefore termed <hi>Regiae Leges Eccleſiae: And whatſoever Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons or Laws publiſhed by Convocation would have been of the ſame Force and Efficacy to oblige the Subject, if only by the King with the Advice of his Council.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In particular; The ſeveral Injunctions, Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Declarations and other Edicts and Requirements from Sovereign Power by his Majeſties Predeceſſors, you have in the Injunction of <hi>Edward</hi> 6.1547, and Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> 1559, with Articles of Viſitation thereunto adjoyned. They licenſe Miniſters to preach, and ſuſpend alſo from preaching. There were Articles in the Time of <hi>Edward</hi> 6. for eſtabliſhing an Agreement in Religion, and the rooting out Diſcords in Opinion 1552, and by Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> 1562. Alſo <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. eſtabliſhed a Liturgy, or publick Form of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to be uſed throughout the Kingdom 1547, 30 <hi>Eliz.</hi> after there had been an uniform Order of Divine Service, and to be uſed only in the Engliſh Tongue, eſtabliſhed by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the only Form, and no other, or otherwiſe: the Queen <hi>Anno</hi> 1560, by her Sole Authority publiſhed a different Form for Funerals, with Liberty to ſay it in the Latin Tongue, with a <hi>Non obſtante</hi> in reſpect to the former Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment.</p>
                  <p>There were alſo Sermons or Homilies, a part of Divine Service, required to be read by the Miniſter, which being a matter of Eccleſiaſtical Cogniſance, were appointed by <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> 6, and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and not by Authority in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. King <hi>James</hi> by his Sole Power, without Authority of Parliament, giveth out Directions for Preachers under Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50015:15"/>of Suſpenſion, <hi>ab officio &amp; beneficio,</hi> wherein many great and neceſſary Goſpel-Truths are forbidden to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by any under the Degree of a Biſhop or Dean. Some Truths may not be preached by way of poſitive Doctrine, but only by way of Uſe and Application; no Sermons in the After-noon throughout the Kingdom to be preached from any Text, but what is taken out of the Catechiſm, Lord's Prayer, Creed, or ten Commandments.</p>
                  <p>He gives Faculties, and confirms a new Body of Lectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, or Preachers, throughout <hi>England,</hi> that be neither Parſons, Vicars, nor Curats.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Inſtances, though not expreſs'd of what theſe Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers have diſpenſed with or indulged; yet are pertinent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Account: What Sovereign Power thus put forth in Conſtitutions, Injunctions, Directions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Matters, may in like proportion be exerted in Exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Diſpenſations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As with Parliament, and other Councils veſted with Authority, the Power to repeal Laws and Statutes is as large as that Power by which they enact and eſtabliſh Laws: For example, if King <hi>James</hi> (which is our laſt Inſtance) might by his Prerogative confirm and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh a new Order of the Clergy, he may by the ſame Power diſpenſe with and licenſe ſuch Preachers as now ſeem and are reputed ſo to be. And it follows alſo, if his Power will extend to indulge ſuch Preachers, it will not prove ſhort in reſpect to Hearers, that are as it were new in the way of their Aſſemblies, and indulge ſuch as are not of the ancient Order of the Parochial Congregation of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The like Deductions might be drawn from other of thoſe Inſtances. I ſhall notwithſtanding for further Confirmation add other Inſtances, and ſuch wherein you have this Power
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50015:15"/>put forth in diſpenſing and exempting from what hath been burdenſom to Mens Conſciences from Parliamentary or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Impoſitions.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. in the fourth Year of his Reign, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Proteſtants removing themſelves and Families out of Popiſh Countries into <hi>England</hi> for their Conſciences Sake, and being not free to ſubmit to the Form of Worſhip and Diſcipline eſtabliſhed in this Church: This good King by his Sole Authority granteth them the Liberty of ſuch a Church-Government and Form of Worſhip (as we ſhall ſay more to in its place) as ſhould be moſt ſuitable to their own Perſwaſion: This being utterly againſt the Proviſion and Settlement newly made by Parliament; he ſtrengthens his Grant by a <hi>Non obſtante</hi> the Statute, and ſtrictly requires all Biſhops and Majors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to ſuffer them quietly to enjoy their Conſciences.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Another Inſtance you have of the ſame good King; <hi>John Hooper</hi> being choſen Biſhop of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> and there being certain Rites and Ceremonies eſtabliſhed by Act of Parliament to be conformed unto in the Conſecration of Biſhops, offenſive to his Conſcience: <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. requires Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> to omit theſe Ceremonies, diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging him of all manner of Dangers, Penalties and Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures he ſhould run into, and be in any manner of way, by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of the ſame; and theſe our Letters (faith the King) ſhall be your ſufficient Warrant and Diſcharge therefore.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Inſtance you have alſo in what was done by Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> for relief of tender Conſciences, namely, her Majeſty being informed that in certain Places of this Realm, ſundry of Her Subjects called to the Miniſtry, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing induced by ſiniſter Perſuaſions, are ſcrupled about the Form of an Oath, which by an Act of the laſt Parliament was preſcribed to be taken according to the Form expreſſed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50015:16"/>in the Act, under Penalty of being diſenabled to bear any Office in State or Church. Her Majeſty was graciouſly pleaſed to aſſume by her Power in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, to give and declare ſuch a Senſe and Conſtruction of the Words of this Oath, expreſſed in other Words (much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent) for their Satisfaction, with a gracious Declaration, That ſuch Perſons fit for the Miniſtry, as could not take the Oath in the Parliament-Form, ſhould accept it in this Senſe, and doing ſo, they ſhall notwithſtanding be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by her Majeſty as good and obedient Subjects, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quits them of all manner of Penalties contained in the ſaid Act, againſt ſuch as ſhould refuſe to take the ſame. By which means many an able Man had Freedom to exerciſe his Miniſtry, which otherwiſe muſt be laid aſide: which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of hers, although againſt an Act of Parliament, yet was owned (as done by Lawful Authority) and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogniſed by the Parliament 5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> and her Expoſition aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to and enacted.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. This renowned Queen, together with King <hi>James</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, confirmed the Indulgence and Diſpenſation granted by <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. to Strangers, yea though it was a <hi>Gravamen</hi> to the Biſhop, making an evident Breach upon the Pale of Uniformity; for not only the Parents, but the <hi>Children, and Childrens Children</hi> which were natural Subjects to his Realm, Perſons of great Eſtate, and Purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of Lands, and intereſſed in the Soil. The Number alſo of theſe Congregations increaſing, and ſcituated in the eminent and chief Towns and Cities in the Kingdom, there to live and profeſs as ſeparated and divided Bodies in Diſcipline and Worſhip from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> was not inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the firſt Grant: ſo Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> complains (there being only that one in <hi>London</hi> when the firſt Grant was made) ſuch things were frequently ſuggeſted againſt them, yet theſe Princes were graciouſly diſpoſed notwithſtanding
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50015:16"/>the Act for Uniformity from time to time to confirm the Grant of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. by ſeveral. Orders paſt, ſome of them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as having ſpecial reſpect to ſuch Objections which will not be amiſs, for the Reader's confirmation, here to inſert ſome of them at leaſt.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="Royal_charter">
                     <body>
                        <head>The Form in which Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> confirmed their Liberties.</head>
                        <p>Non Ignoramus variis Eccleſiis varias &amp; diverſas jam ab initio Chriſtianae Religionis ſemper fuiſſe Ritus &amp; Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonias non contemnimus veſtras, neque nos ad noſtras cogimus.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="Royal_charter">
                     <body>
                        <head>King <hi>James,</hi> Octob. <hi>17. 10 Jac.</hi> to the Dutch at <hi>Colcheſter.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>His Majeſty granted their Orders, Liberties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in as large and ample manner, to all Intents and Purpoſes, as heretofore they have been uſed, tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, and allowed unto them, any Proviſion or Juriſdiction to the contrary thereto in any wiſe not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="Royal_charter">
                     <body>
                        <head>An Order of King <hi>James,</hi> under his Signet, <hi>Jan. 13. 1616,</hi> on their behalf.</head>
                        <p>Theſe are therefore to Will and Command all our
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50015:17"/>Courts of Juſtice, and other our loving Subjects, to permit and ſuffer the ſaid Strangers <hi>and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="Royal_charter">
                     <body>
                        <head>The Order of the Council for the <hi>Walloons</hi> of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> Octob. <hi>10. 1621.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>Thoſe of <hi>Norwich,</hi> though born in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſhall continue to be of the ſaid Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſubject to ſuch Diſcipline as hath been by all the time of fifty five Years practiſed by them.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="Royal_charter">
                     <body>
                        <head>The Order of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, <hi>Novemb. 13. 1631.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>We Will and Command our Judges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit and ſuffer the ſaid Strangers, <hi>and their Children,</hi> quietly to enjoy all and ſingular, &amp;c. without any Troubles, Arreſts, or Proceedings, by way of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, or otherwiſe.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="Royal_charter">
                     <body>
                        <head>An Order of the Council for the <hi>Dutch</hi> of <hi>Norwich,</hi> Jan. <hi>7. 1630.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>That all thoſe that now, or hereafter ſhall be Members of the Dutch Congregation, although born within this Kingdom, ſhall continue to be of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50015:17"/>the ſaid Church, ſo long as his Majeſty ſhall be pleaſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>Theſe and divers the like Inſtances might be produced, which ſufficiently evince it as granted on all ſides, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly ſuppoſed to be according to the Conſtitution of this Realm, that our Kings and Princes have Power, in and from themſelves, as an inherent and inſeparable Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, not only to injoin and give Laws to their Subjects in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, (ſuch as are left to the ordering of any Civil Power) as alſo to diſpenſe and exempt from Laws of that kind, though eſtabliſhed by them in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the Authority of Parliament.</p>
                  <p>Nor do we find that Parliaments at any time have taken into Conſideration, what was ordered or done by thoſe Kings and Princes in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, being their known Prerogative; no not in thoſe of King <hi>James,</hi> who aſſumed the moſt in ſuch managements; nor by any Petitions or Addreſſes to any of thoſe Princes, which is uſual in the Concerns of Civil Rights, for limiting or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging the Exerciſe of their Power in theſe Eccleſiaſtical Matters, but rather recognizing and confirming what hath been ordered by them, as in 5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and <hi>Car.</hi> 2. in the Act of Uniformity; and other Inſtances many may be produced.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:50015:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Objections made againſt this Power, and the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting thereof, with Anſwer thereunto.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THere are Reaſonings poſſibly tending another way in ſtating this Caſe: The Objections obvious I ſhall now mention, having divers material Conſiderations pertinent to a more full and clear ſtating this Caſe, which might have been produced in the Body of this Diſcourſe, but are reſerved rather to this place, partly, becauſe we find this vulgar way of Dialogue, lets in Knowledg with leſs diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty; and what is required by way of a Queſtion, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gageth him that propoſeth, with greater attention to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what is ſaid in the Anſwer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>QUEST. I.</hi> If ſuch a Prerogative be in the King, what need Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Laws be tranſacted and eſtabliſhed by Parliament?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That hinders not but that his Majeſty's Power is ſufficient of it ſelf to do many things relating to ſuch Laws without them; take it in his Majeſty's own words, Declarat. of 26 <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1662. <hi>To concur with us in making
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50015:18"/>ſome ſuch Act as may enable us to exerciſe with a more univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Satisfaction, that Power of Diſpenſing which we conceive to be inherent in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</hi> As alſo it is by the afore-named learned Judg <hi>Hubbard</hi> expreſſed, That <hi>theſe Statutes, and the like, were made to put things in ordinary Form, and to eaſe the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign of Labour, but not to derogate from his Power.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Powers ſufficient in themſelves may join, and in ſuch conjunction remain intire, as Powers Cumulative, and not Privative; as it is evident from what is ſaid in the Statute of 31 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. <hi>The King's moſt excellent Majeſty, though it appertained to his Prerogative Royal, to give Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as it ſhall ſeem to his Wiſdom; he is nevertheleſs plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and contented for an Order to be had,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>by this High Court of Parliament, that it ſhall be enacted by the Authority of the ſame,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The King is a kind of Corporation in himſelf, diſtinct from that Capacity wherein he ſtands in conjunction with his Subjects as their Head: And in that reſpect, being in an higher Region, above, and in a greater diſtance from thoſe Intereſts, upon the account whereof his Subjects are many times much divided, and publick Edicts are formed according to the Prevalency of a greater Party, to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of others that are his Loyal Subjects alſo; by his Wiſdom and Prudence there is a Ballance, by which the Tranquillity of a Nation is happily preſerved, and one Party is not overborn by the other, having this Power to mitigate and diſpenſe in the Matters under our conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as in his Wiſdom, with Advice of Council, ſhall ſeem equal.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:50015:19"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. 2. QUEST. II.</hi> But hath not the King's Prerogative Limits in our Laws? And are there not ſome Things which he cannot diſpenſe with, no not with a <hi>Non Obſtante?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> I grant it, and in ſeveral Caſes.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. He may, by ſpecial Words in the Statute, bind up himſelf from making any uſe of his Prerogative.</item>
                     <item>2. In what is <hi>Malum in ſe,</hi> in reſpect of Impiety or Unrighteouſneſs.</item>
                     <item>3. When ſuch Diſpenſations are deſtructive to the great Ends of a Common-Wealth, Common Juſtice, the Proprieties of Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. To the firſt; His Majeſty, or any of his Predeceſſors, hath not at any time, in any Statute or Law that concerns theſe Eccleſiaſtical Matters, by any ſuch ſpecial Words bound up himſelf, but rather the contrary, as in thoſe two Acts wherein more eſpecially our Affair lieth: That for Uniformity, where the diſpenſing with that Statute gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Strangers, by ſole Prerogative-Authority, is juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. And the Act of 22 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. by the <hi>Proviſo</hi> there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, the Parliament ſeems to induce his Majeſty's Aſſent in the recognizing of his Prerogative, ſo expreſly in that Act, as if they ſpoke thus: Though this Act be very Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, yet if it be found prejudicial, or not to attain the End for which we judg ſuch Severity to be requiſite; it is an Eccleſiaſtical Affair, and your Majeſty may, when you pleaſe, diſpenſe and exempt Perſons from it.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:50015:19"/>
                  <p n="2">2. There is nothing tranſacted in theſe Eccleſiaſtical Affairs by the Civil Magiſtrate, and as depending on his Authority, but ſuch Matters as in the ſenſe of our Law are things materially indifferent, and therefore not <hi>Malum in ſe,</hi> they do not bind <hi>the Conſcience of the Subject, in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of them, conſidered in themſelves,</hi> (Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments 1569, Preface) <hi>the keeping or omitting of a Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in it ſelf, is but a ſmall thing, yet the wilful and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous tranſgreſſion and breaking a common Order,</hi> &amp;c. So that theſe Precepts concerning Eccleſiaſtical Matters, oblige not in their own Nature, as what is either <hi>Bonum</hi> or <hi>Malum in ſe,</hi> but as prohibited or commanded.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Civil Rights and Claims, and in Temporal Things only, are of the immediate and intrinſick Concern and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of all Republicks, <hi>Dominium non fundatur in Gratiâ;</hi> if the juſt claim of a Prince may not be interrupted, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account he is of this or that Religion or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion; nor may a Subject be juſtly Baniſhed, Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, Confiſcated or Ruined, upon the meer account of Religion, or becauſe his Conſcience is not caſt into the ſame Mould with the Prince or preſent Eſtabliſhment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. 3. QUEST. III.</hi> Religion, and the Worſhip and Service of God, being the great Concernments of a Nation; Is it not then to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence with the Penalties in Eccleſiaſtical Laws, too great a Truſt to be repoſed in any one Hand?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. In what ſenſe Religion is the Concern of a Civil Republick.</item>
                     <item>2. The Nature of this Truſt.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:50015:20"/>
                  <p n="1">1. The Moment or Weight of a Matter in our delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, hath its proportion, either as under an abſolute or reſpective Conſideration; <hi>Wiſdom is better than Riches</hi> in it ſelf, but not in relation to the ſupport of preſent Life; the Knowledg of God, and Divine Things, is better than to know the Virtue of Drugs and Plants, but not ſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the ſtudy of Phyſick: ſo Religion, and the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, is the chiefeſt and better part in it ſelf conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; but in its reſpective Conſideration, as to the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a particular Perſon, to a Community of Men for the advance of Civil Affairs. There are other Qualifications and Inducements of greater conſequence, and more direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and immediatly tending to the being, or well-being thereof.</p>
                  <p>That there be no Miſtake in this great Concernment, I further diſtinguiſh; There cometh under the Notion of Religion, the Holineſs and Righteouſneſs that is of the Moral Law, Principles whereof are in all Mens Natures, and attend in their Actings by a natural Conſcience.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Goſpel-Duties directed and ordered by a Supernatural Light, no Foot-ſteps or Principles hereof are found in us. For the former; Religion in that ſence, as the Knowledg of God, Conſcience of an Oath, Juſtice and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in our Dealings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are ſuch Things wherein the Well-being of Common-Wealths is much concerned. But Religion, as it ſtands in the exerting Supernatural Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and in Duties termed the <hi>Commandments of Chriſt,</hi> (as the other the Commandments of God, <hi>John</hi> 15.) as Faith, Repentance, Sacraments, Diſcipline, and the like Goſpel-Ordinances: In the Duties under theſe Heads conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and as diſtinct from Moral Duties, there is little or nothing directly and immediately contributed by them to Mens Civil Intereſts, further than where theſe Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50015:20"/>Vertues are planted in Mens Minds, the Moral Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Piety and Honeſty do more plentifully abound, and are in exerciſe. As thoſe Morals do more immediatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Republick, ſo the Laws thereof are principally drawn forth out of them; eſpecially Second-Table Duties, forming and moulding them into municipal Laws, under Penalties and Incouragements, greater or leſs, as in the Wiſdom of a State may conduce moſt to the Welfare there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For theſe Goſpel-Myſteries it's otherwiſe; for as they contribute little to us in our Civil Government, otherwiſe than as before mentioned; ſo is there little contributed by the Wiſdom or Authority of any State, advantagious to the Goſpel, but Protection, or being a Defence upon this Glory. Learned Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> ſtates it well; <hi>Princes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>command, that which Chriſt the Sovereign Lord and Head of the Church commandeth, which is all the Power we give to Princes.</hi> (Of Supremacy, <hi>pag.</hi> 227.) And in the Page before, thus; <hi>By Governors in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, we do not mean Moderators, Preſcribers, and Magiſtrates bearing the Sword, to permit and defend that which Chriſt himſelf firſt ordained and appointed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to return;</p>
                  <p>If <hi>Adam</hi> had ſtood, all Common-Wealths would have been proſperous and flouriſhing; and yet, no Chriſt, no Faith, nor Repentance, nor any Goſpel-Worſhip known or practiſed: And ſince the Fall, you have had well-governed Common-Wealths of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> that never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Chriſt, or Goſpel-Worſhip. It is with States, as it is with particular Perſons in converſe; another Man's E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, or Trade, or Credit, or any Civil Concern with whom I have to do, is not prejudiced or bettered by my omiſſion or practice of what is a meer Goſpel-Duty. If a Man I deal with, be unjuſt, lie, ſteal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> my worldly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50015:21"/>Intereſt is prejudiced hereby; but whether he repent for this, exerciſe Faith on Chriſt for Forgiveneſs, and humble himſelf, I am neither a gainer nor loſer hereby, in the ſenſe we ſpeak of.</p>
                  <p>Now it is Goſpel-Worſhip we profeſs in this Nation, Goſpel-Religion. If the Duties themſelves performed are of no greater conſequence in reſpect to Perſons with whom we converſe, or the Civil State where we live, the Modes, Forms, and Ceremonies of ſuch Worſhip, cannot be of ſuch moment or truſt in the manage of them: And let me add, much leſs can there be any ſuch ſpecial advantage to our State-Concernments, in this or that particular exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Form of Worſhip or Government, that it ſhould be retained by us with ſo much Zeal and Contention; which evidently appears in this, how proſperous and flouriſhing hath this Nation been in their Civil Concerns under Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, ſet Liturgies, Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and as great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity in other Chriſtian Republicks, where theſe have been altogether diſallowed.</p>
                  <p>Nor is this any diſhonour to the Goſpel, more than to the Kingdom of Chriſt, when it was ſaid <hi>not to be of this World,</hi> or to his Perſon, or Offices, that they contribute no more to the ſetling of Civil Rights and Intereſts, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.13. or to Goſpel-Weapons, which being Spiritual, and not Carnal, have no Edg to cut off Mens Liberties, Eſtates, or Lives.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Nature of this Truſt.</p>
                  <p>The Laws and Inſtitutes by which theſe Eccleſiaſtical Matters are to be managed, are appointed and eſtabliſhed for Subſtance, by the Wiſdom and Authority of that one Law-giver Chriſt Jeſus: The Application of theſe Laws, in reſpect of Circumſtances, for the well and comfortable enjoying Goſpel-Ordinances, is all that any Humane Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50015:21"/>hath to do in them, the Truſt whereof may be placed in the Hand of a wiſe and prudent Prince.</p>
                  <p>Again. There is liberty of an after-Judgment to be made by him; that is, to practiſe in what-ever is of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of Religion, commanded by Men. Thence ſuch Laws require not ſuch ſimple and peremptory Obedience, if conformable to thoſe Rules required in the Word. Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience thereunto is with reſpect to God, as well as Man; if otherwiſe, that choice ought to be left to the Subject, which the Apoſtle claimed, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.29. Although Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, and the Concerns of it, be great Things conſidered in themſelves, and accordingly is the Truſt, yet what of it falleth under the Hand of a Civil Power, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in it ſelf, is not ſo.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe the greatneſs of this Truſt ſticks generally in Mens Minds, eſpecially when in the diſpoſal thereof it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the Will of one Man. To remove this or the like Stumbling-block, we will ſuppoſe failings in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Truſt, as great as rationally can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Suppoſe his Majeſty ſhould refuſe, either by Himſelf or Parliament, to enjoin any thing of Ceremony, or Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance about theſe Ceremonies and Externals, the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Service of God.</p>
                  <p>Or, 2. ſuppoſe he ſhould diſpenſe with all Injunctions, and leave the People of God to their Liberty in the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of them: the Premiſſes laſt mentioned being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, there can be no great prejudice to the Common-Wealth, or Civil Affairs thereby. Diſtinctly we ſhall weigh each of theſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For the former; <hi>If the keeping or omitting of a Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, in it ſelf conſidered, is but a ſmall thing, as we men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before, and of ſuch a nature, as although at firſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50015:22"/>'twere of Godly Intent, and purpoſely deviſed, yet at length turned to Vanity and Superſtition, and burdened Mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences without cauſe,</hi> &amp;c. as we our ſelves acknowledg, <hi>(See Preface to Common-Prayer Book).</hi> And of the ſame condition are moſt of thoſe Impoſitions which have proved burthenſom to the Nation a long time; and if ſo, the not impoſing of theſe things cannot be prejudicial to Church or State. Not to the Church; if theſe Directions for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Worſhip, in the external Circumſtances of it, were not reduced into Canons and Injunctions, but left where they are to be taken up in practice according to the Light of the Age; as are Goſpel-Duties of great Conſequence. Thoſe Scriptures by which States profeſs themſelves to be guided in the forming of theſe Eccleſiaſtical Laws, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted alſo in the Hands of his Goſpel-Miniſters, for their conduct and direction in ordering Goſpel-Affairs; who have Gifts and Aſſiſtances from Chriſt, in ſuch a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and degree, as cannot be expected in the ableſt Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, as ſuch. And the Eccleſiaſtical Laws are never ſo well ordered by Civil Powers, as when they conſult with, and take advice and direction from the Miniſters of the Goſpel about them.</p>
                  <q>To adviſe new Rites and Ceremonies (<hi>ſaith Biſhop</hi> Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) is not the Prince's Vocation, but to receive and allow ſuch as the Scriptures commend, and as the Biſhops and Paſtors of the Place ſhall adviſe. <bibl>(<hi>Of Suprem. p.</hi> 226.)</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p n="2">2. If there were no ſuch ſevere Injunctions about the Forms and Modes of Goſpel-Worſhip, (I ſpeak not of ſuch Duties of Religion in which Mens Natures are prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled.) 1. The Nation could not hereby ſuffer in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of its Civil Concerns but the Wealth and Trade, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> much more proſperous. The Things being ſmall in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and become great only upon the account of their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50015:22"/>being injoined, and the greatneſs of Penalties annexed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of great concernment to the State, that is, to the great prejudice thereof, as hath been apparent in many Years ſad experience. What is it of moment to Common-Wealths for the quickning of Trade, keeping up of Rents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or any particular Man's Civil Concern, that Men kneel or not at the Sacrament, croſſing or not, croſſing in Baptiſin? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. For the other; A diſpenſing with all Penalties an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to Eccleſiaſtical Laws; where theſe Penalties are removed, yet theſe Laws remain as Counſels and Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements, and being conſulted by the Learned Clergy in their Synod, and commended as uſeful in the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Worſhip, this is as much as ever was done by the Apoſtles, when Churches were in their greateſt purity, who endeavoured not ſo much to eſtabliſh an External Uniformity, as to preſerve Chriſtian Liberty.</p>
                  <p>If it be ſaid, They had then no Chriſtian Magiſtrates. 1. We ſay, The Kingdom of Chriſt muſt come into a Nation, before it be Chriſtian; and if it be ſo defective in its firſt addreſs, for want of ſuch a Magiſtrate, and of the Means we put ſo great an Eſteem upon, for reducing a People, how will the People ever become Chriſtians? And on the other ſide; if the Goſpel hath a ſufficiency in it ſelf, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out borrowing) to ſubdue a Pagan Nation to Chriſtianity, much eaſier it is, being ſuch, to preſerve them orderly and regular Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> having inſtructed and counſelled, left his People free, <hi>and to the perſwaſion in their own hearts,</hi> Rom. 14.5. <hi>One Man eſteemeth one day above another, another Man eſteemeth every day alike: let every Man be fully perſwaded in his own mind.</hi> That was but a Counſel or Advertiſement. In the Act for Conformity, in 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> given to the Arch-Biſhop,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50015:23"/>Biſhops, and other Ordinaries, that they would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to perform their Duties in the Execution of that Act; it was indeed very ſolemn, that is, from the <hi>Queen's Majeſty, the Lords Temporal, and all the Commons in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament, and in God's Name, and as they will anſwer before God for ſuch Evils and Plagues, as may be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the neglect thereof.</hi> There hath been no want of Obedience hereunto by the Biſhops, being fully perſwaded in their Hearts hereof as their Duty; of which, if they had not been ſo perſwaded, the ſevereſt Penalties would or ought to have been in vain.</p>
                  <p>King <hi>James</hi> orders, throughout the Kingdom, that the Afternoon's Exerciſe, each Lord's Day, be ſpent in exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining Children in their Catechiſm, inſtead of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This is only commended as the moſt convenient and laudable way of teaching in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that ſuch Preachers be moſt encouraged and approved of: And how readily was this immediatly practiſed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Nation? and is continued in many places to this day.</p>
                  <p>In the Eſtabliſhment of Uniformity, 2 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty was left in reſpect of Ceremonies, to practiſe or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them, according as Men were perſwaded in their Hearts.</p>
                  <p>By the Synod held 1640, ſome Rites there mentioned are heartily commended by them, to the ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all good People, as an Ancient and Laudable Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the Primitive Church in the pureſt Times. And notwithſtanding all this extolling thoſe Rites, (which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is as much as can be ſaid for any of our Ceremonies) the Canon concludes thus; <hi>In the practice or omiſſion of this Rite, we deſire that the Rule of Charity preſcribed by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles may be obſerved; which is, That they who uſe their
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50015:23"/>Liberty, deſpiſe not them which uſe it not; and they who uſe it not, condemn not thoſe that uſe it.</hi> (Can. 7. 1640.) And this their counſel and commending hath not been in vain, but received and ſubmitted unto throughout the Nation, by thoſe who were ſo perſwaded of theſe Rites, as they have commended them: And ſo would it have been in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of other the Rites of our Church. And the free ſubmiſſion in practiſe of a Rite, though but from a fewer number of grave and pious Perſons, would have advanced the Eſteem of ſuch Rites and Ceremonies in the Opinion of others, much more than the forced ſubmiſſion of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Numbers.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As a farther Anſwer, let us conſider the Nature of the Crime, with reſpect to the Penalties. The Crime, as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in our Laws, is a wilful and obſtinate, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous omiſſion, as 1 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 2. in the Act of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niformity;</hi> where theſe words, <hi>wilful</hi> and <hi>obſtinate,</hi> I would think are not deſcriptive, and to be underſtood <hi>reduplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> as an Aggravation; and as if all Omiſſions muſt of neceſſity proceed from Wilfulneſs and Obſtinacy, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctive, and to be underſtood <hi>ſpecificative,</hi> ſome Omiſſions being from Wilfulneſs and Contempt; but there may be Omiſſions that are not ſo, and being not ſo, fall not under the Penalty, as killing a Man, and wilful Murder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the words of that Act, 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Edicts, would ſo be underſtood, there are theſe Reaſons.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. We would not ſuppoſe this Law to be grounded upon ſo hurtful a Principle as this, That where a difference of Perſwaſion, in relation to a difficult Caſe of Conſcience, that one Party is always wilful and obſtinate, there is not a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50015:24"/>greater uncharitableneſs, and more oppoſite to that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Love and Peace we ought to endeavour after.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It was not ſo judged by our Governors in that Age, when this Act of Uniformity (1 <hi>Eliz.</hi>) was eſtabliſhed, but a more charitable Interpretation of Mens ſcrupling Obedience; as is evident from the Relief given to ſuch by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who, with the Advice of her Council, put forth a Book of Articles to be enquired of at the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and Preſentations to be made accordingly; and of 56 in number, there was not among them one about ſuch Rites and Ceremonies then eſtabliſhed, that were offenſive of purpoſe, as ſome judg, to abate the Rigour of that Act, and other Injunctions, which ſhewed they were not all Wilful and Obſtinate that could not Conform. Some Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Biſhops, after this Example, framed their Articles of Enquiry with more moderation; and divers Miniſters not fully conforming, enjoyed their Miniſtry under them: The more ſevere Clergy, obſerving the Liberty enjoyed more in ſome Dioceſſes than in others, made this Proviſion in the Synod, 1640, <hi>Can.</hi> 9. That for the better ſetling of Uniformity, there ſhould be but one Book of Viſitatory Articles, that the more moderate and indulgent Biſhops might not have the forming their own Articles. The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Biſhops themſelves, did not judg that all Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity was from Wilfulneſs; nor would thoſe many Diſpenſations and Exemptions before-mentioned, be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our Governors, if they had judged thoſe who came not up to the Eſtabliſhment, diſobeyed out of Obſtinacy and Contempt, nor ſuffer ſome of them, as Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> did, to preach before her in her Chappel.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:50015:24"/>
                  <p n="3">3. That all Eccleſiaſtical Tranſgreſſions, even in Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that are little in themſelves, are from Wilfulneſs and Obſtinacy, (what this Act ſuppoſeth, if ſo interpreted) is a Maxim in Diſcipline, neither Chriſt nor Chriſtian Churches were ever acquainted with. Chriſt in his Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Proceedings againſt Sinners, diſtinguiſheth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Sin it ſelf conſidered, and as a Sin wilfully and obſtinately committed, and hath appointed Means for the diſcovery hereof; and if the Sin be of Infirmity, a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Procedure, and a more tender Dealing is appointed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. and not to apply Cenſures, and cutting off, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of Wilfulneſs and Obſtinacy; only we are willing to believe ſuch is (I am ſure ought to be) the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of our Proceſs in theſe Matters, and what appertains to the Worſhip and Service of God, profeſſing ſo frequently as we have done, That we take the Word for our Guide in the eſtabliſhing theſe Eccleſiaſtical Laws.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Our Lawgivers judg the Pureſt Churches, thoſe of the Primitive Times, were Voluntary Congregations of Believers, (as we ſaid before out of Judg <hi>Hobbart</hi>) ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting themſelves to Paſtors as God ſhould move them, no Patrons then impoſing upon them. Now there is no voluntary Act to which we are moved, but ſuch motion is upon the account of ſomething that is real or appearing Good. There is no rational Man can voluntarily join and become a Member of a Society or Congregation in ſuch condition within his Partioipation, which is probable to be of greater Evil than of Good: It will be ſo with us, if this Act be interpreted <hi>Reduplicative,</hi> that is, whoſoever omits a Ceremony, doth it obſtinately, and ſhall ſuffer as ſuch an one. I join voluntarily, in hopes to be edified in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50015:25"/>Knowledg, Zeal, Tenderneſs of Conſcience; and where ſuch Attainments are, there is a greater aptneſs to ſcruple Obedience to ſome one Thing or other injoined; which if we do, we are ruined or undone, firſt or laſt, ſo ſevere are the Penalties in the Proceſs of them, whether Miniſter or private Chriſtian: it will not be with a Man, (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>if he will depart, let him depart</hi>) to loſe the Privileges upon the account whereof we joyned, which is the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty enjoyed in all Corporations and Societies, but muſt abide upon the place, and look on, while all be deſtroyed: What rational Man upon Election, and voluntarily will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one in ſuch a Congregation? And this is the real and juſtifiable Ground of Separation, upon the account where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of many thouſands of ſober and peaceable Perſons have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, not only from our Communion, but their Native Country, for the advantage of that purer and primitive Order of a Voluntary and free Congregation.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In the Statute of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> it's not ſimply the refuſing, or not uſing the Forms there injoined, but the doing it wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully or obſtinately; Or, that the keeping or omitting of a Ceremony, in it ſelf conſidered, is but a ſmall Thing, as we mentioned before. I grant, Matters very ſmall, being made the Subject of a Penal Law, or injoined for State-Ends, may thereby become great; the ſmaller the Matter is in it ſelf in ſuch a Caſe, the greater is the wilfulneſs in tranſgreſſing, and ſo may juſtly demerit a greater Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: But yet a Matter being ſmall in it ſelf, and as it ſtands the Subject of a Political or Civil Law; the ſame when it becomes the Matter of an Eccleſiaſtical Law, ought not to be formed with reſpect to State-Ends, or <hi>in ordine ad Temporalia,</hi> though it be a ſmall Matter in it ſelf, and as a thing meerly Natural or Moral, may
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50015:25"/>notwithſtanding be very great upon that account, and greater to the Perſon who ſcruples the Lawfulneſs thereof, than the greateſt Penalty that can be incurred by refuſal; for there is no Circumſtance or Ceremony, that hath a conſtant Station and Place in the Worſhip of God for any Spiritual End deſigned (as ours are) but in their relation, and reſpect thereunto, are great, what-ever they are in themſelves. Theſe Laws therefore being Eccleſiaſtical, wherein God and Mens Conſciences are ſo immediatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted, the not conforming to them cannot be ſuppoſed a true meaſure to judg of Mens Wilfulneſs or Obſtinacy; it would be a great reflection upon the Prudence (or the Charity at leaſt) of our Laws and Injunctions ſo to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret them.</p>
                  <p>If the greatneſs of the Penalty be ſaid, not upon the Crime materially conſidered, but in reſpect of that evil Frame wherein we tranſgreſs, God only is the ſearcher of Hearts; and although by Overtures and Circumſtances, ſomething may be diſcovered this way, yet it is with great difficulty and uncertainty, eſpecially when we tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs by Omiſſion: the reaſon is, in poſitive Acts done by a Man, all the Faculties of the Soul are engaged, and exert themſelves together at the ſame time; and in the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of ſuch acting, there remains thoſe Overtures of ſuch a frame of Mind, as a more permanent and exact Counterpart thereof. Omiſſions are many times when the Mind ſtands but half-bent, the Underſtanding not clear, the Will not determined; in an Omiſſion there is nothing of the Man left upon Record diſtinctly to be read and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered of by us, ſo that we can ſcarcely ſo much as gueſs from what Principles within an Omiſſion doth proceed. And the uncertainty is far the greater, when it is noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly known, ſuch Omiſſions may be from a good Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50015:26"/>as well as a bad. To be able ſo far to dive into Mens Hearts, as diſtinctly to diſcover Intentions, is a Work more ſuitable to the Word of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. than the Laws of Men; we would not therefore interpret theſe Laws in ſuch a ſence, as to render all Omiſſions to be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Principles of Wilfulneſs and Obſtinacy: it would be more charitable, where ſo little Evidence can be produced, rather to judg the contrary of our Brethren and Fellow-Subjects.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. This Act of Uniformity (not we hope in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of it, but in ſuch an Interpretation) hath been the Original of all our Sufferings. If therefore that be not the true meaning of the Act intimated in his Majeſty's gracious Declaration, namely, That upon what Principles ſoever Men ſubmit not unto it, though from tenderneſs of Conſcience in the greateſt Evidence, yet thereupon to be puniſhed with the loſs of all their Spiritual Promotion: but if it appear from Obſtinacy and Sedition, that ſuch on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhould ſuffer ſo deeply, by the addition of further Pains and Penalties as are in that Act inſerted, what is more juſt and equal? If this yet be not the meaning of the Act, as it ſeems by conſtant Proceedings againſt the Tranſgreſſors of it; for what Man was ever relieved in any Court Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical or Civil, upon ſuch a Plea, he omitted not ſuch Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations wilfully, but of Conſcience? I ſay therefore, If that be not the ſenſe of the Act, yet upon theſe Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations but now mentioned, there is Evidence ſufficient, that this gracious Diſpenſation of his Majeſty, of ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundant Penalties (and of ſuch a Nature) are all the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties we are exempted from in that Declaration, is to be judged of as moſt Neceſſary, Prudent, Juſt, and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:50015:26"/>
                  <p>His Majeſty being therefore perſwaded, that <hi>many Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes</hi> (it's his Majuſty's Expreſſion, <hi>Declart.</hi> of <hi>Dec.</hi> 26. 1662.) ſuffered, being inſnared in their Conſciences, and not from Wilfulneſs; and his Charitable Opinion ſeems to be grounded upon an Obſervation of his own: <hi>It is evident</hi> (ſaith his Majeſty) <hi>by the ſaid Experience of twelve Years, there is very little Fruit of all thoſe forcible Courſes.</hi> The Will is a more unſteady Principle, and eaſily wrought to a Change upon Repreſentation of Good or Evil. But Conſcience is more fixed and incorrigible, it not being in our own Power to alter the Dictates thereof: as to be changed from our Natural State, was not in our Power; no more is the change of our Perſwaſions in Matters of Duty, Conſcience being engaged, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15. but God alone doth it. His Majeſty therefore wiſely judged it would be leſs Injuſtice, and better for the Common-Wealth, that all ſuch Penalties be removed, and ſuſpended, when the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of them have been ſo conſtantly miſapplied, and ſo much to the prejudice and diſquiet of his Good Subjects. It is Righteouſneſs, and not Ceremonies, that Eſtabliſh a Nation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:50015:27"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. 3. QUEST. IV.</hi> If the Penalties of all Eccleſiaſtical Laws be removed, theſe Laws themſelves become impracticable; and when Men are left to worſhip in what Forms they pleaſe, will not that Ancient Eſtabliſhment, of one Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Worſhip and Government to be the ſame through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Kingdom, be utterly deſtroyed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. For that which we term Uniformity in the Worſhip and Service of God, we find no other in the Apoſtolical Churches, but what aroſe from inward Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, freely and naturally, theſe Principles being the ſame: as where there is the ſame Seed, there will be the ſame Blade, Stalk, Leaf, Flower. And there is an Uniformity from External Impreſſions, as in a Mould, theſe are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, and forced. The former, is from the Lord, a Work of his Power, and there is beauty in it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. The latter is from Princes and States, wrought by the Power of their Laws and Penalties, and may have much hypocriſy, but little amiableneſs. The baſeſt Metal, as well as pure Gold, will conform to the Mould into which it is caſt. Such a conformity is no ſafe Character to diſtinguiſh who is fit, and who not, for Miniſtry or Memberſhip; but the other is of great uſe in the Churches of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>As the Wicked, who are a Seed of Evil-doers, are uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form in their Practice, being acted from the ſame inward Principles, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.17. So the People of God being <hi>bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed into one Spirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. <hi>They live in this Spirit, and walk in this Spirit,</hi> Gal. 5.25. And as in other Duties of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50015:27"/>Piety and Juſtice: So in Church-Adminiſtrations, where Men are of the ſame Mind and the ſame Principle, they will all ſpeak the ſame things, though not the ſame Words, in Preaching, in Praying, and Officiating in the Service and Worſhip of God, though there be no external Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts, or force of Humane Laws, to bring Men to an exact conſcientious Uniformity in the Externals of Worſhip and Ceremonies, where there are various Apprehenſions; this is not to be effected by the moleſting of Men in their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Eſtates, judging or cenſuring, or indeed by any humane Power; God himſelf that can do it, and eſtabliſh Men in ſuch an Uniformity, yet for Ends ſutable to his Wiſdom, leaves them various in their actings in this kind; one Man obſerving a Day, or the like Ceremonies, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obſerves it not; but moſtly ſtanding upon ſincerity in thoſe that practice, doing, or leaving undone, <hi>to the Lord,</hi> that is, out of Conſcience; and this is the Apoſtolical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5.</p>
                  <p>That which we term Uniformity, an exact Indentity in Words, Geſtures, and Veſtments, Nature ſeems to teach us an example of a ſinleſs neglect of; though there be a conformity in every Vine, and every Fig-tree, and the like works of Nature, one to another in their kind, yet for the Modes, and outward Form and Shape, you have not two of theſe that are conformable, and grow alike.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Nor can we ſay, but though all the Penalties (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſuch) annexed to Eccleſiaſtical laws, are removed; yet there will remain proviſion ſufficient left in our Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, both to keep and preſerve Men in Conformity, that are ſo, and to reduce ſuch as are not ſo: for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty hath been graciouſly pleaſed, as on the one hand, <hi>to aſſure the Orthodox-conformable-Clergy, that they ſhall receive and enjoy the Revenues belonging to the Church of England,</hi>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:50015:28"/>(the richeſt, moſt plentiful, and ample of any Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church in the World) <hi>and that no Perſon, though diſpenſed with in other things, ſhall be exempt from paying his Tythes, and other Duties whatſoever.</hi> And on the other hand, <hi>That no Perſon ſhall be Capable of holding any Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, Living, or Eccleſiaſtical Dignity or Preferment of any kind in the Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>who is not exactly confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable.</hi> Such Encouragements are alſo <hi>Privitive</hi> Penalties, and have brought and kept more to Conformity, than all the Penalties removed by his Majeſty's Declaration.</p>
                  <p>When was it known that a Biſhop, or Dean, or double<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beneficed Parſon, left his Promotion and became Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt; and others that have been bred up to Literature, at great Charge, having Gifts and Parts, would be ſo peeviſh as to refuſe, being hereupon forced to divert from the way of a more free Education, to ſome mean Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment to get a lively-hood, or live upon the Charity of others? (It is the Condition of hundreds this Day in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land);</hi> And can we imagine any Men having ſuch Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements in their Eye, and the more deſirable from ſenſe of their preſent Indigency, keep off, but from Integrity of Heart?</p>
                  <p>His Majeſty, as a Common Father, hath the ſame Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections for all his Good Subjects, and never more prudence and tenderneſs manifeſted by any Prince, than be hath done in this his Gracious Declaration. One Party, ſuch as Conform, injoy their Conſciences with ſpecial Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in Temporal Things; the other, they alſo enjoy their Conſciences, with Freedom from thoſe Severe Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and theſe are fatisfied alſo. And now let not any Man's Eye be Evil, becauſe his Majeſty hath been ſo good to their Brethren.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:50015:28"/>
                  <p>Let me ſay again, That his Majeſty hath in Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Prudence, done a great Work, and that which hath lain undone, to the diſturbance of his good Subjects, more or leſs, ever ſince the Reformation; That is, in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying, or laying a ſufficient ground of Satisfaction to the two great Parties which divided this Kingdom, in the Matters appertaining to Religion; That is, in the Forms and Ceremonies of Worſhip, (In the Profeſſion of Faith, and Articles of Religion, according to the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 13. <hi>Eliz.</hi> there is one Union in the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of both Parties) and this without the leaſt detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or juſt prejudice of either Party; Thoſe that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, enjoy their Conſciences, imploy their Talents, and reap the Encouragements of the eſtabliſhed Government, without any loſs or detriment to thoſe that conform not; And this party, enjoy their Conſciences and Freedom from ſuffering, and liberty to follow their Callings, without the leaſt damage to the Conformiſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. 5. QUEST. V.</hi> Is there any neceſsity his Majeſty ſhould exert a ſole Power in Affairs of Religion, when the Peace and Unity of the Nation herein was undertaken by his Parliament, and many Things endeavoured that way by them, and Purpoſes (its likely) of a further progreſs therein?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> For Anſwer, it will be neceſſary to inſert here briefly a Narrative of ſome Paſſages of his Majeſty and the Parliament in theſe Proceedings.</p>
                  <p>His Majeſty obſerving how Affairs ſtood here in this Kingdom, and the Diſtractions that were on Mens Minds about Religion, and Forms of Worſhip; and conſidering
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50015:29"/>there are but two ways ſuppoſed ordinarily to reduce a People again to Peace and Unity in Religion; (1.) Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſeverity to diſcourage and extirpate; Or, (2.) by lenity and indulgence to bear with Diſſenters. His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty conſidering thoſe Forms and Ways of Worſhip, to which Conformity is now required, have not only been much ſcrupled, and contended againſt by Learned and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Men, ever ſince the firſt Reformation; but of late ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly disfavoured by a Repreſentative of the Nation, and a Synod of Learned Men. And different practices in the Service and Worſhip of God, by the preſent Powers that then were encouraged; and ſuch which were not other but what was received and obſerved in the beſt Reformed Churches Abroad, and by the Dutch and French Churches here at Home. Upon theſe and the like Conſiderations, his Majeſty choſe, upon great Deliberation, the way of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; it being alſo moſt ſuitable to his Conſcience, and ſweetneſs of his Nature.</p>
                  <p>This is Reſolution he profeſſed to all the World, and engaged himſelf by promiſe to his People, he would endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the effecting thereof; which is more than evident in the many Declarations he made hereof, and repeated again upon all Occaſions. He was pleaſed, in a Declaration from <hi>Breda, to anſwer a Liberty to tender Conſciences; and that no Man ſhall be diſquieted, or called in queſtion, for Differences of Opinion in Matters of Religion, which do not diſturb the Peace of the Kingdom.</hi> And in his Speech, <hi>July</hi> 17. 1660. profeſſeth that he owes his Being here to God's Bleſſing, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Intentions and Reſolutions he had and expreſſed in that Declaration. This Declaration his Majeſty afterwards (<hi>May</hi> 8. 1661.) terms a <hi>Promiſe ſolemnly made:</hi> This Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or Promiſe is ſo much upon his Royal Heart, that he tells both Houſes, (<hi>July</hi> 8. 1661.) that ſo oft as he comes to them, <hi>he mentions his Declaration from</hi> Breda, <hi>that Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50015:29"/>as well as they might mind it.</hi> In his Majeſty's Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 26. 1662. he tells us, <hi>That he remembers the very words of the Promiſes from</hi> Breda, <hi>that concern Liberty of Conſciences, and the Confirmations he hath made of them ſince, upon ſeveral occaſions; and as all theſe Things are freſh in his Memory, ſo he is ſtill firm in the Reſolution of perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to the full. Feb.</hi> 10. 1661. in a Speech to both Houſes; <hi>One Thing more I hold my ſelf obliged to recommend unto you at this preſent, which is, That you would ſeriouſly think on ſome Courſe, to beget a better <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Compoſure in the Minds of my Proteſtant Subjects in Matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; whereby they may be induced to ſubmit quietly to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and moſt faithfully give their Aſſistance to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>His Majeſty did not only expreſs his Purpoſes for the eaſe of Tender Conſciences, but from time to time endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it. And firſt of all, by a Declaration (<hi>Octob.</hi> 25. 1660.) to all his Loving Subjects of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi> concerning Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, mentioning that from <hi>Breda,</hi> diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with the uſe of divers Ceremonies formerly injoined, that were offenſive. <hi>March</hi> 25. following, he gave Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to certain Learned Divines to meet at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and take the Service-Book under conſideration to the ſame purpoſe. <hi>May</hi> 11. 1661. frees from their Impriſonment ſuch as ſuffered for Conſcience.</p>
                  <p>The King and his Parliament happily joined in the ſame pious End, Peace and Union, yet differenced in their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of the Means to procure it; which was our great unhappineſs. The Parliament judged the reducing and rooting out Diſſenters, by ſevere Penalties, to be the means of Unity in the Church, as they tell his Majeſty in Anſwer to his Declaration; <hi>Preſſing the aſſerting of the Laws and Religion, eſtabliſhed according to the Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50015:30"/>as the more probable means to produce a ſet led Peace and Obedience throughout the Kingdom:</hi> Suppoſing (and poſſibly ſome of them perſwaded thereunto, from thoſe that never would diſtinguiſh betwixt Conformity and Sedition) the diſſent of Nonconformiſts from the preſent Eſtabliſhment, to be rather from a Spirit of Faction and Diſloyalty, than Tenderneſs of Conſcience, proceeded accordingly. The Act of Uniformity was renewed, and the Service-Book in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined, with no alteration of what was formerly offenſive in it, but ſome Expreſſions of greater difficulty to be digeſted by thoſe that were Tender, and nothing done yet in what his Majeſty had promiſed in way of relief to Tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</p>
                  <p>Hereupon not only multitudes of faithful Preachers of the Goſpel in the ſeveral Shires of this Kingdom, were put from their Imployment, but alſo the Minds of Men much diſturbed, and filled with hard Thoughts and Jealouſies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Account. Inſomuch that his Majeſty was inforced to publiſh that Declaration of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 26. in which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes the Surmiſes of the People, occaſioned by this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity; thus, That <hi>having made uſe of ſuch ſolemn Promiſes from</hi> Breda, <hi>and in ſeveral Declarations ſince, of Eaſe and Liberty to Tender Conſciences; inſtead of performing any part of them, we have added ſtraiter Fetters than ever, and new Rocks of Scandal to the Scrupulous by the Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity.</hi> To this Surmiſe and Jealouſy, his Majeſty condeſcends to make Reply thus; <hi>As concerning the Nonconformance of our Promiſe, We remember well the very words of thoſe from</hi> Breda, <hi>(repeating the words) and the Confirmations we have made of them ſince, upon ſeveral Occaſions in Parliament; and as all theſe Things are ſtill freſh in our Memory, ſo are we ſtill firm in the Reſolution of performing them to the full. But it muſt not be wondred at, ſince that Parliament to which thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50015:30"/>were made in Relation to an Act, never thought fit to offer us any to that purpoſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Houſe of Commons took his Declaration into conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and repreſented to his Majeſty divers Objections againſt it, and laid it aſide, ſo that nothing was effected thereby to his Majeſty's Purpoſe; the Parliament being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe minded, and certainly it is not only their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but Duty, to proceed in reforming Abuſes by ſuch Means as are in their Perſwaſion moſt ſuitable and likely to be effectual, otherwiſe they could not be faithful in their Truſt. Greater Severities againſt Nonconformity are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, in ſeveral Acts upon occaſion, as the Act againſt private Meetings, 16 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. The expelling Miniſters five Miles from Burrough Towns, 17 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. Eſpecially that Act of 22 <hi>Car.</hi> intituled, <hi>An Act to prevent and ſuppreſs Seditious Conventicles;</hi> An Act very high and heavy in the Penalties expreſſed, both upon Miniſters and People, his Majeſty notwithſtanding condeſcended to give his Royal Aſſent to that Bill. It being judged this Severity was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up by them from good Intentions, and as the likelieſt means of Peace and Union; as alſo if it proved not to be ſo, that they might be yet more fully convinced of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency of ſuch a way, having had hitherto, for ſome Years, experience how little effectual it hath proved.</p>
                  <p>Yet this Bill containing nothing for ſubſtance, but what was proper to his Eccleſiaſtical Power, being an ordering the Externals of the Church, and nothing of immediate Concern in Civil Affairs in the whole Act: And his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty having intentions to take the other Courſe, if this of Severity effected not what was aimed at, a Proviſo is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Act, in theſe words; <q>Provided alſo, that neither this Act, nor any thing herein contained, ſhall extend to invalidate or avoid his Majeſty's Supremacy
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50015:31"/>in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs; but that his Majeſty, and his Heirs and Succeſſors, may from time to time, and at all times hereafter exerciſe and enjoy all Powers and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, as fully and amply, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or any of his Predeceſſors have, or might have done the ſame, any thing in this Act notwithſtanding.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>As this Act of 22 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. was very ſtrict and ſevere in it ſelf; ſo the execution of it, was with much Violence and Rigour in moſt parts of the Nation, there being Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made in it, ſuch, as even looſe and indigent Perſons may intrude themſelves in the promoting thereof, with encouragement not only of their Luſts gratified in perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting thoſe they ſo much hate, but their Neceſſities ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied from large Rewards for the ſame; Having Power gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to inform againſt Juſtices, Mayors, Conſtables, and ſuch as are intruſted in the Execution hereof, who are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der great Fines and Penalties, for Omiſſions limited in this Act, and the Informer to have a Moiety hereof himſelf. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that by the rigorous execution of it, thouſands of his Majeſty's good Subjects were utterly ruined. Perſons induſtrious and diligent in their Callings, driven from their Habitations, their Houſes broken open, their Goods imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeled; the Materials of their Trades, the Tools they wrought with, and the Beds they lay upon, ſeized and ſold; Trade every where decayed, Rents of Land fallen, Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty coming on like an Armed Man; Perſons haled from theſe Meetings for the Worſhip of God, through the open Streets, to Priſons, being of the ſame Faith with us, and ſo peaceable and unblameable in their Converſation, as that nothing could be objected againſt them but in the Matters of their God; nor for any thing upon that account, but their endeavouring to practiſe as thoſe Reformed Churches, we our ſelves own for ſuch, and hold a Brotherly Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with as the true Churches of Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:50015:31"/>
                  <p>The Nation generally being thus diſtracted and diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, thoſe in Power going on ſtill to make Laws to afflict and puniſh, and others engaged quietly to ſuffer whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they ſhould be expoſed to for their Conſciences: Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters being at this paſs, there was apparent neceſſity that ſome Remedy be ſpeedily applied.</p>
                  <p>His Majeſty conſidering they are all his Subjects, and how much by ſuch Severity the Intereſt of his Soveraignty is narrowed, ſo great a number of his People rendred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of his Countenance and Protection, and upon no other Account or Crime, but their being of different Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions in ſome Externals of Religion, Perſons otherwiſe for Induſtry, Faithfulneſs, Loyalty, and every way qualified to do his Majeſty and their Country as much Service as others.</p>
                  <p>His Majeſty alſo calling to mind that prudent Caution which his Royal Father left him in theſe words; <q>Take heed <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> that outward Circumſtances and Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities in Religion, devour not all or the beſt Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Learning and Induſtry, but with an equal Eye, and impartial Hand, diſtribute Favours and Rewards to all Men, as you find them for their real Goodneſs, both in Ability and Fidelity, worthy and capable of them; this will be ſure to gain you the Hearts of the beſt, and moſt too.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was likewiſe impoſſible for his Majeſty to imagine that ſo many thouſands (in his own Obſervation) who have ſuffered ſo greatly with ſuch humble ſubmiſſion, ſhould daily thus expoſe themſelves and Families to ruin, from no other or better Principles than a Spirit of Obſtinacy and Stubbornneſs; great Sufferings, and by great Multitudes, yet no Tumults, no Reſiſting, whereas in the beginning of the Reformation, what Armies in the North, and in the Weſt,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50015:32"/>upon this Account, by thoſe of another Perſwaſion, were raiſed, tho as yet they ſuffered little?</p>
                  <p>His Majeſty, as a Common Father, beareth Affection to all his Subjects; but who of them deſerves it, and who not, can never be diſcovered by this indiſcriminating Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity; that is, who are Diſſenters upon Principles of Conſcience; and who of them ſo pretending, are notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of a Seditious Spirit?</p>
                  <p>Theſe can never be diſtinguiſhed one from the other, when Diſſenters, and ſuch as Conform not, be it upon what ground ſoever, are all of them equally branded with the ſame Mark of Diſloyalty, and ſo repreſented to his Majeſty, and all the Nation: There is a neceſſity that this Pretence of Conſcience be removed, and Seditious Perſons diſcovered, and left to condign Puniſhment; and others (theſe Stumbling-blocks being removed) may, by their peaceable Obedience to all other his Majeſty's Laws, juſtify and vindicate their Integrity; which can no ways be done, while the Righteous are thus condemned with the Wicked; and no relaxing thoſe Laws, that ſhut up all, both Guilty and Innocent, under the ſame Condemnation.</p>
                  <p>Of theſe Things his Majeſty hath had a clear proſpect all along, and thence publickly declared his avowed readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (in his Proclamation <hi>July</hi> 16. 1669. and otherwiſe) to indulge Tender Conſciences; and hath, upon the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, and the like weighty Conſiderations, been ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to publiſh this his Gracious Declaration of <hi>March</hi> the <hi>25th,</hi> 1671, wherein he hath fully performed his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made at <hi>Breda,</hi> and ſo often repeated. Thus his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, as a Wiſe and Prudent Prince, whoſe Station is fixed in an higher Orb, (like the Sun exhaling and conſuming, or turning to refreſhing Showers the dark Fogs and Miſts here beneath) hath, by the Light and Liberty ſhining
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:50015:32"/>forth from his Gracious Indulgence, refreſhed multitudes of his Good Subjects, and delivered them from the dark miſapprehenſions of others. Nor is this their great Relief in any thing prejudicial, either to the Eſtates or Liberties of Men otherwiſe minded; nor are ſuch Men abridged in any of their Concerns, Spiritual or Temporal, hereby; his Majeſty hath made ſufficient Proviſion for the ſatisfying their Conſciences, in a careful continuing thoſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Forms of Worſhip they have been accuſtomed to; let it not be grievous or offenſive unto them, that their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren have obtained the like favour from his Majeſty in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their Conſciences.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle requires, That we neither judg or deſpiſe thoſe that differ from us, in Matters of the like Nature; but to leave a Man without moleſtation from us, to his own Maſter, to whom he ſtandeth or falleth; his being in the right, or in the wrong (upon this account) is a Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Maſter's concern, What is it to us? What have we to do to diſcipline another Man's Servant, for what his Maſter is pleaſed to bear with him?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:50015:33"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. 6. QUEST. VI.</hi> Since theſe Eccleſiaſtical Laws of Reſtraint were enacted by Parliament, the King giving his Royal Aſſent, had it not been convenient, if his Majeſty had ſo pleaſed, that the diſpenſing with theſe Laws had been by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The Kings and Princes of this Realm, his Majeſty's Predeceſſors, did Eſtabliſh many Things and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by Parliament, relating to Eccleſiaſtical Things; but did yet nevertheleſs often exerciſe their own Power in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſing with the Penalties of ſuch Laws. A conſtant act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with others in the exerting hereof, might (though no Preſcription againſt the King) yet introduce at leaſt in the Minds of Men a kind of ſuſpicion, eſpecially in the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, that ſuch Proceedings of the Supream Majeſty by his ſole Power, to be an aſſuming an Arbitrary Government.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Parliament did ſtill continue in this their former Opinion and Judgment, namely, That a way of Severity was the only Means to ſettle Peace and Unity. They had newly paſſed the Act for Uniformity, without any abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of what was Offenſive; by reaſon whereof, aroſe that general Diſcontent which before we have mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                  <p>His Majeſty being ſenſible hereof, did, by that Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 26. move a ſecond time, <q>That an Act might be prepared, whereby he may be enabled with a more univerſal acceptation, to exerciſe the Power of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſing, which is inherent in him, not doubting their
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:50015:33"/>chearful cooperation with him, being a Matter wherein he conceived himſelf ſo much engaged, both in point of Honour, and in what he oweth to the Peace of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, which We profeſs <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> we can never think ſecure, whilſt there ſhall be a colour left to the Malicious and Diſaffected, to inflame the Minds of ſo many Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes upon the ſcore of Conſcience, with diſpair of ever obtaining any Effect of our Promiſes for their Eaſe.</q> 
                     <hi>The Houſe returns this Anſwer,</hi> 
                     <q>We your Majeſty's dutiful and loyal Subjects, who are now returned to ſerve in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from thoſe ſeveral parts and places of your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, for which we were choſen, do humbly offer to your Majeſty's great Wiſdom, That it is in no ſort adviſable that there be any Indulgence to ſuch Perſons who <hi>preſume</hi> to diſſent from the Act of Uniformity, and the Religion eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, for divers Reaſons, whereof this is one; It will in no wiſe become the Gravity or Wiſdom of a Parliament, to paſs a Law at one Seſſion for Uniformity, and at the next Seſſion (the Reaſons of Uniformity continuing ſtill the ſame) to paſs another Law to fruſtrate or weaken the Execution of it.</q> So that now his Majeſty had no other Remedy, but either.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To retract from that pious and ſeaſonable Reſolution for Liberty of Conſcience, expreſſed in Letters to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament then ſitting, from <hi>Breda,</hi> a Reſolution ſo accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to them, as the whole Houſe, <hi>Nemine contradicente,</hi> by Letters returned him Thanks, and bleſs the Name of the Lord, who put ſuch reconciling thoughts into the Heart of the King; and he himſelf likewiſe owns an eſpecial Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from God upon his Affairs, after he had expreſſed that Intention.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or break that Promiſe he ſolemnly made, aſſuring this Liberty; and had profeſſed to the World upon this
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50015:34"/>Occaſion, in his Speech <hi>May</hi> 8. 1661. that he valued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf much upon keeping his Word, and whatſoever he promiſed to his Subjects, and that no Man can be his Friend, and wiſh him well, who would perſwade him to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the breach of that ſolemn Promiſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Or leave the Nation under greater Diſtractions and Sufferings about Religion than he found it in; and upon twelve Years experience of other means uſed, which tended rather to increaſe the Diſtemper.</p>
                  <p>Theſe diſhonourable Things, I ſay, his Majeſty muſt have ſuffered and undergone, or make uſe of that Power God and the Nation have intruſted him with, though not with concurrence of Parliament, ſo much and ſo often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by him, <hi>even ſo oft as He came to them,</hi> as he tells them in his Speech of <hi>July</hi> 8. 1661. Yet nothing at any time was done by the Houſes, in reſpect to Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, being obliged in their Judgments to proceed in the other way.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of former Examples for Indulgence.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HIS Majeſty's Gracious Declaration contains not a greater Indulgence; tho it be extended to a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number of Perſons, than what was granted by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Predeceſſors (which before we have mentioned) to the French and Dutch Congregations.</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:50015:34"/>
                  <p n="1">1. There was a Uniform Order in Church-Government and Divine Service, to which not only his Majeſty's Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but all the Inhabitants of his Majeſty's Dominions were to conform, and no Man to abſent himſelf: And not to hear or be preſent at any other Forms of Prayers, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Sacraments, than what is in that Book pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, under Penalties of Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures, Fines to the King, to the Poor of the Pariſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Diſpenſation and Exemption was by the ſole Authority of the Soveraign, and ſtands thus; A Liberty to ſeparate and abſent themſelves from the Pariſh Aſſemblies, where they had their Habitations, and to gather themſelves into diſtinct particular Churches or Congregations, to chuſe and ordain their own Miniſters; alſo to eſtabliſh ſuch a Church-Government, or Diſcipline, and Form of Worſhip and Divine Service, as they amongſt themſelves judged to be moſt conformable to the Scriptures, eſtabliſhed by his Majeſty's Patent as a Corporation within it ſelf, and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent upon any Superior Juriſdiction Spiritual but his Majeſty's: And all Biſhops, Mayors, Sheriffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect them, and ſuffer them quietly to enjoy and exerciſe theſe Liberties, with a <hi>Non Obſtante,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Grounds and Conſiderations upon which ſuch Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Exemptions were granted, were theſe:
<list>
                        <item>1. The Care of Religion that ought to be in all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Princes, and to be ſhewed forth eſpecially in this, the Relief and Incouragement of thoſe that are of the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, in their Sufferings for Conſcience of their Duty towards God.</item>
                        <item>2. Perſons of the ſame Religion with us, and Sacraments adminiſtred by them, according to the Word of God, and practice of the Apoſtles, ought to be tolerated in their
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:50015:35"/>way of worſhipping God, though they differ from us in Ceremonies and Diſcipline.</item>
                        <item>3. The Kindneſs we found in other Proteſtant Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, when we were forced to leave our Native Soil for preſerving our Conſciences.</item>
                        <item>4. There were alſo great Advantages in Matter of Trade, for their skill and induſtry, to the great benefit of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and prejudice of their own. L. <hi>Herbert</hi>'s Hiſtory of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Premiſes conſidered, we further ſay;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. His Majeſty's Proteſtant Subjects here ſpoken for, to whom this Gracious Indulgence is extended, are of the ſame Religion with others of his Subjects, and the preſent Eſtabliſhment, in reſpect to Matters of Faith and Worſhip in external Forms; alſo they are not more differing from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> than thoſe Congregations to whom the ſame Indulgence hath been granted by his Majeſty and Predeceſſors, and is ſtill enjoyed.</p>
                  <p>And when thoſe Strangers had removed their Families, and come among us, had not this gracious Indulgence been granted and continued to them, their Conſciences would have engaged them to depart hence, and ſeek Habitations where the like Liberty might be obtained. And this alſo is our Condition; many hundreds of his Majeſty's Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, with their Families, have left their Native Country, and diſpoſe themſelves into other parts of the World upon the ſame account.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If it be ſo grateful a Charity, and deſerving ſo ſolemn an Acknowledgment, the kind Entertainment our Subjects have found in other Parts, when not ſuffered to live in their own Land, upon the account of Conſcience, doubtleſs it is a greater Charity to be ſo indulgent to our own, as not by Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity to enforce them for Conſcience to become Strangers in other Countries.</p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:50015:35"/>
                  <p n="3">3. And for Matter of Trade, Advantages have been great by encouraging thoſe Strangers; but the Diſadvantages in the ſame kind far greater by the late Severity, by which our own Subjects have been ſo greatly diſcouraged; not only thoſe Hands hang down, that were moſt induſtrious in hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the ſtaple Trade of the Nation; but by reaſon of Artificers removing into other Parts for their Conſciences, the Myſteries of our chiefeſt Manufactures have been made common, and others therein become equal, if not exceed us: A great ſenſe hereof his Majeſty hath expreſſed in his Gracious Declaration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> If it be ſaid, <hi>Theſe be Strangers, Objects of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, being driven out of their own Country, underſtood not our Language, they were Educated and accuſtomed to other Forms of Diſcipline and Worſhip.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It's true, the firſt Grant of this Liberty was to ſuch; but in proceſs of Time, theſe Churches were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed and ſpread throughout the Nation; and this Grant being confirmed by Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> K. <hi>James,</hi> and K. <hi>Charles</hi> I. to their Children, Engliſh born, and born Subjects of this Realm, they had the ſame Liberty granted them as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was mentioned; inſomuch, as the Perſons now enjoying this Liberty, are his Majeſty's Native Subjects.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. The greateſt number of his Majeſty's Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Subjects, that have benefit by his Gracious Indulgence ſince they have had underſtanding, have been trained up in, and been acquainted with no other Forms of Diſcipline and Worſhip, than what was found amongſt us at his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's return, the other, formerly eſtabliſh'd, having been for many Years totally diſuſed. King <hi>James</hi> himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing educated under other Forms, when he came into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:50015:36"/>ſcrupled many Things in our Liturgy and Rubricks. <hi>Conference at</hi> Hampt. Court. Finally;</p>
                  <p>It is now more than a Century of Years, wherein theſe Churches have enjoyed this Indulgence; there hath been much peace and quiet among themſelves, following their Callings without diſturbance; neighbourly and friendly Converſe with thoſe that are of different Perſwaſions in Matters of Religion.</p>
                  <p>No Diſputings or Reaſonings about it, no Judging or Deſpiſing; experience hereof we have, beyond denial, in <hi>London, Norwich, Canterbury,</hi> &amp;c. where diverſity of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, in the Forms of Diſcipline and Worſhip, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly held forth in the view of all Men for ſo many Years. And why ſhould not we expect the like peaceable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive Converſe mutually between thoſe that now enjoy the like Liberty, from this Gracious Declaration, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of our Brethren, whoſe practice is otherwiſe.</p>
                  <p>The Lord, who hath put this into the Heart of the King, may put it alſo into the Hearts of our Senators to be like-minded with him. And as his Majeſty hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended to them in their way for the ſpace of theſe twelve Years, (as he tells them); ſo it is to be deſired that they (if it may ſtand with their great Prudence) would concur with him but half ſo long, in the way himſelf hath choſen, for the Peace and Union of his Subjects in Matters of Religious Worſhip; or at leaſt until there be the like evident Experiments of the Ineffectualneſs of it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>
               <hi>The ſame Author hath publiſhed a Book, intituled,</hi> The Lawfulneſs of the Oath of Supremacy, and the Power of the King in Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Affairs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With a Vindication of Diſſenters, proving, That their particular Congregations are not inconſiſtent with the King's Supremacy. With ſome account of the Nature, Conſtitution, and Power of the Eccleſiaſtical Courts. Sold by <hi>Jo. Robinſon,</hi> and <hi>Sam. Crouch.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
